<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vox clamantis, or, A cry to Protestant dissenters calling them from some unwarrantable ways, with which they are vulgarly, and perhaps too truly charged, viz. from all unnecessary medling in matters of state, from too deep engagement of themselves in this present world, and too great conformity to it : from thinking too highly of themselves for their separation-sake only : from fanaticism, properly so called, in their prayers, sermons, books, &amp;c. : and seriously exhorting them to the minding of the great concerns of heaven, to fruitfulness in well-doing, to sobriety, and the use of reason in all religious matters / by N.N. a Protestant and declared dissenter from the Church of England, as far as that church dissents from Christian liberty, to holiness and charity, and no further.</title>
            <author>N. N., Protestant and declared dissenter from the Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 194 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52918</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N63</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5934</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12025051</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12025051</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52640</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52918)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52640)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 571:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vox clamantis, or, A cry to Protestant dissenters calling them from some unwarrantable ways, with which they are vulgarly, and perhaps too truly charged, viz. from all unnecessary medling in matters of state, from too deep engagement of themselves in this present world, and too great conformity to it : from thinking too highly of themselves for their separation-sake only : from fanaticism, properly so called, in their prayers, sermons, books, &amp;c. : and seriously exhorting them to the minding of the great concerns of heaven, to fruitfulness in well-doing, to sobriety, and the use of reason in all religious matters / by N.N. a Protestant and declared dissenter from the Church of England, as far as that church dissents from Christian liberty, to holiness and charity, and no further.</title>
                  <author>N. N., Protestant and declared dissenter from the Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 82 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W.H. and are to be sold by Richard Janaway,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52640:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Vox Clamantis; OR, A CRY TO <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters,</hi> Calling them from ſome unwarrantable Ways, with which they are vulgarly, and perhaps too truly charged, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From all unneceſſary medling in matters of State.</p>
            <p>From too deep engagement of themſelves in this preſent World, and too great Conformity to it.</p>
            <p>From thinking too highly of themſelves for their Separation-ſake only.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Fanaticiſm,</hi> properly ſo called, in their Prayers, Sermons, Books, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſeriouſly exhorting them to the minding of the great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of Heaven.</p>
            <p>To Fruitfulneſs in Well-doing.</p>
            <p>To Sobriety, and the uſe of Reaſon in all Religious matters.</p>
            <p>By <hi>N. N.</hi> A Proteſtant, and declared Diſſenter from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as far as that Church, diſſents from Chriſtian Liberty, Holineſs and Charity, and no further.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 12.2.</hi>
               </bibl> Be not conformed to this World.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 18.</hi>
               </bibl> If it be poſſible live in peace with all men.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Theſſ. 4.11.</hi>
               </bibl> Study to be quiet, and to mind your Buſineſs.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. H.</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>Richard Janaway, Anno Dom.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:52640:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52640:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>VOX CLAMANTIS,</hi> OR, A Cry to the Profeſſors and Diſſenters of this Age, in <hi>England, London,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Chriſtian Friends and Brethren,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have heard, and you can't but know; that many ſerious minded Chriſtians, much lament the great decay of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and ſerious Piety, among the Profeſſors of this Age; and thoſe that are called Diſſenters, herein <hi>England,</hi> and in this City in ſpecial: And enquiring into the Cauſes of it, they ſeem to be divers, beſides that common and general one of a careleſs Spirit, which all are too apt to fall into, even in the moſt weighty things, and the things of God, and of their everlaſting concern: which being matters inviſible and future (though moſt real) we conſider not, but are taken up too much with the preſent things of ſenſe and outward appearance, becauſe neareſt to us, and ſo moſt affecting of us: I ſay, beſides this in the general; there are ſome preſent ſpecial cauſes, reaſons and occaſions, that are bad, and at beſt ſcandalous, which it is the intent of this preſent call and advice to remind you of, and to admoniſh you, that they are detrimental, and hinder your progreſs and perſeverance, in well-doing, in order to your eternal well-being. And if we do but look into the ſtate of this Age, and the Land we live in, as to the profeſſion practice of Religion, and the Chriſtian Religion, it is ſad,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52640:3"/>and to be lamented by all, who have any ſenſe of the maine concerns of Chriſtianity; or of mankind.</p>
               <p>The world of profeſſing Chriſtians in this Nation, (to look no further) are found to be of two general ſorts: The</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Are the ungodly, openly prophane; who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they have been born and educated in this moſt Holy Religion of Chriſt Jeſus, yet carry nothing but the name of it; and who, becauſe they have not had the hap to now another, muſt needs be called Chriſtians; yet live in all manner of open ſin, committing all ſin with greedineſs, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Whoredom, Drunkenneſs, Swearing, Lying, Acts of Violence, Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and all manner of Debauchery; and theſe things not only in ſecret, but openly; yea, and that which I think few Ages have ſeen, (ſince Chriſtianity) openly owning and avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vileſt abominations, fleſhly, carnal luſts and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and that ſometimes in the moſt publick manner: This is, and hath too much been the guiſe and practice of evil men, of great men in place and power; and ſuch evil examples pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate wonderfully, and beget in their own nature and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs dayly, even to admiration. Theſe ſeem as if they would, or had a mind induſtriouſly to propagate ſin and wickedneſs, and to declare themſelves to be the open and ſworn ſervants of ſin and the Devil. If it were in their power, and they ſhould accordingly make Laws to promote and advance the moſt wicked abominations and filthy luſts, they could not that way do half ſo much towards it, as now by giving ſuch pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and open examples. It is the moſt effectual way to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Vice, and that with the greateſt advantage, as to the debauching and eternally ruining of others; when perſons great in power and place, give ſuch examples. As our Lord teaches us, that the moſt effectual way to glorify God, is not ſo much to Preach and Profeſs, or tell the vertues of our Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father, as to imitate and follow them; and that the light of our good and excellent works, ſhining before men, will tend infinitely more to the glory of God, and is a better proof of the truth of our Chriſtianity, and of our good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience Godward, than any aſſent or ſubſcription whatſoever, to the beſt Syſtem of Divinity, Articles of Faith, or Modells
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52640:3"/>of Worſhip, which the evil and hypocrite may do, as well as the beſt, and moſt ſincere. To be holy, upright, juſt, ſober, and to mortify and ſubdue the luſts and pollutions of the fleſh, that fight againſt the Soul and Spirit, this is the hard work, that few ingage in, though it be all in all, as to the life and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Chriſtian man. But we are now ſpeaking of a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of men, into whoſe hearts ſuch things do not enter, or once come into their thoughts; or if they do, they ſoon ſhake them out, and get rid of them, being reſolved rudely and madly to put all to a deſperate adventure, and never to try nor make enquiry into things of this nature, into the truth of Chriſtianity; till they feel it in their own damnation. But enough of theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> There are another ſort, profeſſing Chriſtianity, that are better than thoſe, (at leaſt not ſo apparently bad) that ſeem to have eſcaped the groſs pollutions of the World through luſts, and cannot be charged with ſuch open abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, but in general are Sober, Religious, and in many things Zealous; great hearers of Sermons, frequenters of Churches and Meetings: Yet it is too apparent, that they ſometimes pride themſelves exceedingly in thoſe things, and are highly conceited of themſelves, becauſe they are not ſo bad as the worſt, and will confidently ſpeak againſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thoſe that are openly wicked, and glory that they are not like other men; and ſo comparing themſelves with the worſt, think themſelves wondrous good; but in this they take wrong meaſures, the right way is to look up to the beſt, to ſee how they come ſhort of them, <hi>i. e.</hi> of the moſt commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and approved Servants of God and Chriſt Jeſus, the holy Apoſtles, the Prophets, and the life and example of Jeſus him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and not to mind how much better they are than the worſt, or the moſt. Notwithſtanding this, that yet ſuch the Profeſſors and Diſſenters of this Age are much wanting, and in many things out of the way, is too plain to be hid; and all take ſome notice of it, their enemies do it to their reproach, thereby to repreſent them both falſe and hypocritical, and alſo ridiculous. That they do well, that do ſo, I am far from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52640:4"/>thinking; but that you ſhould not mind, and take warning by it, and upon this occaſion look well to your ſelves, and into your ways, ſearch your own hearts and works, examine your principles and practices; this I think argues great careleſsneſs, and neglect, and ſhews that you have not that fear nor care, which you ſhould have, nor a mind truly ſet within you, to deſign the honour and glory of God, nor the credit of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
               <p>I have divers times upon occaſion told (and others have done the like) ſome of the Profeſſors of this Age, what things and matters, thoſe publick Scurrilous Libels and Pamphlets, that fly about the Streets dayly (with ſome other of more ſober language and treatment, but as venomous) what theſe I ſay do ſtill object, and caſt in the teeth of the preſent Diſſenters; being things and faults that they will needs have to be Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racteriſtical of them all. But when we have told ſome of the Profeſſors of this Age of thoſe matters, to warn and admoniſh them, and to let them know what the things are, that they proclaim as moſt culpable in them, they ſtill reply; that ſuch are enemies, a ſort of looſe, ungodly, and prophane men, ſcoffers at Religion, turning all into ridicule, and ſo not to be heeded or regarded in what they ſay. Be it ſo; what then? Though you will not mind it for their ſake, yet you ſhould for your own, and for the Name of God, the credit of Religion and of your own Party (for unhappily we are diſtinguiſhed into Parties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> God forgive thoſe who in any kind are the cauſers of it.)</p>
               <p>But do you not remember the old ſaying <hi>(Ab hoſte fas eſt doceri)</hi> It is lawful, yea very good and prudent to learn from an enemy. And if it were for my Life and Soul, I would in the firſt place hearken to my enemies when they reprove or find fault. 'Tis true, they are like to over-do, yet moſt like to do that which our neareſt and beſt Friends may be loth to do for us, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſpeak thoſe things to us, and of us, that the Laws of Friendſhip and Civility, and love of our Friends and Party, will not ſuffer them to do.</p>
               <p>I do acknowledge that one benefit I have received in the reading ſuch Papers, has been; that though I ſaw they were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52640:4"/>out, and writ neither with a Spirit of Piety nor Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, nor the leaſt compaſſion to thoſe whom they ſo ſeverely blame, but do it only to render them odious and ridiculous, and to make the looſer ſort of men merry, and indeed to bring them out of the way of the love of ſerious Piety; yet I learn much in them, which otherwiſe I might not ſo well have underſtood. As matters in the world now are, we better ſee others than our ſelves; and as no man can ſee his own face, ſo neither are a mans own works and actions ſo near unto him, at leaſt not ſo open before him, as other mens: Therefore if I can't ſee my ſelf ſo well, I am beholding to thoſe, that ſhall in good will tell me, and ought to acknowledge it with grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. But if they tell it to me or others, not out of love, but ill will, and to expoſe me; however I have the ſame or a greater benefit, and the worſt I will do and return to them, is, to pray God, that ſeeing they have ſpoken againſt me evil, or what they think is ſo, they may alſo ſee their own, and hate all ſin and evil; and this can't hurt them, neither can they for it be angry with me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <p>I Will at preſent inſtance in one thing, becauſe it comes now into my mind; which they do commonly object, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by endeavour to expoſe you to ſcorn, eſpecially the Miniſters and Preachers of the Non-conforming Party; and them the rather, becauſe the People have had, an honourable eſteem of them for their pains and labour in Preaching, and with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to many of them, for their great Faithfulneſs, and doing much good by their Miniſtry. Now to leſſen the Peoples love towards them, by means whereof they are drawn from, and make leſs eſteem of the Conformiſts way; therefore have thoſe men induſtriouſly inſpected, and culled out of the Books and Sermons Preached and written by them, all they could think of, or find abſurd, or ſeeming ſo; that they might thereby
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52640:5"/>render them odious, or at leaſt leſs eſteemed: <hi>E. G.</hi> too vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and over familiar Sayings to God in their Prayers, and the like in their Sermons and Books of Practical Divinity, all their courſe Phraſes, their unfit, uncouth ſimilitudes; all, as they call them, Phanatical Notions and Expreſſions, with ſuch things which they will needs have tend to Sedition and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. Many things of this nature, they cull out, publiſh and expoſe to the World, to be ſeen in their blackeſt colours: They have raked together many Books and Pamphlets of late, and of latter days they ſeem to ply this work more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, and to ſet and imploy witty men, both of the Clergy and Laity therein. I could tell you of many Perſons and Pieces, to this purpoſe deſigned and bent; one of the moſt ſober of them, is the Author of the <hi>Friendly Debate:</hi> And one of the moſt often imployed this way, whoſe profeſſion and buſineſs it is, is Mr. <hi>R. L.</hi> with his Aſſociates: I wiſh that witty Gentleman, would uſe his Parts and Wits ſome other, and ſome better way: For my part, had I the Ability he hath, that quick, ſmart and pleaſant way of Expreſſion, that plenty of free utterance; In ſhort, if I had ſuch excellent rare Endowments as that Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and ſome others have, and are owners of, I think, I durſt not uſe them, in ſuch a Prophane way, and in ſuch uncharitable work, as they and he do. But he muſt give account to God; let him but a little ſeriouſly conſider, with what Spirit he does this; whether it be like to the Chriſtian Spirit, or Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus: And if indeed he really owns the truth of that Religion and Revelation of God by Chriſt, I can't think but that a little reflection upon himſelf, and of this work, will do him good.</p>
               <p>Well, but to you my Friends, and the more ſo, becauſe I know many of you to be Holy Chriſtian men, deſigning God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs: To you I ſay this they do, and would it be now any hurt to you to conſider, whether there may not indeed be ſome of thoſe Errors and Miſdemeanors in ſome of your Books and Sermons; whether there may not be many things obnoxious in thoſe kinds now named, and others which they will ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently inform you of: Conſider of it, with free minds, do not think.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:52640:5"/>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That becauſe they are enemies, and it may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane wits that find fault; that therefore you may conclude nothing is amiſs; but hearken to them (to chooſe) that find great faults, whether real or ſuppoſed, or any likeneſs or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of ſuch matters in your diſcourſes or practices: You would ſurely have them learn from you, I am ſure you would take it well if they would be taught by you, and ſo ſhould you not diſdain to hearken to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> This would ſhew you to be of honeſt, ingenuous minds, and of thoſe that love the Truth, and would much convince the inſulting adverſary of your uprightneſs and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity. What hurt or diſgrace is it, to retract, or to let them know that in ſome things, you may not have been ſo wiſe and wary, but that you may and will amend?</p>
               <p>Look over ſeriouſly and ſee, whether ſome particular no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of yours may not betray you, and make you to ſpeak, write, and preach, not ſo manly, rationally and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, as you might and ought; but things looking too like Phanaticiſm, as they think, and would be glad to find.</p>
               <p>Certainly the Chriſtian Religion does not unman men, but makes them more perfect; it makes good Chriſtians, to be the wiſeſt as well as the beſt of men.</p>
               <p>You are not to think, that becauſe your own Hearers, who out of a good opinion of your worth and Piety, may be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what too credulous, and take all at the beſt, that therefore others will do ſo too. They that Preach and Write about Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Divinity, ſhould regard thoſe that are contrary, and that may be perhaps wicked, but witty, of Parts, but little Piety, of Learning and liberal Education, but not much Charity, and ſo not like to take every thing by the right handle; not to take the beſt meaning and interpretation, the thing will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear. And though men prophanely and ſcurrilouſly call you Phanaticks; yet give them neither juſt cauſe nor occaſion for it, in ſpeaking and preacking of the word of God and Religion. All ſhould mind to do as the Apoſtle adviſes <hi>Timothy</hi> in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Study to ſhew thy ſelf approved to God, a workman that needs not to be aſhamed,</hi> (i. e.) Not aſhamed that men, any men, ſhould hear him (rightly dividing the word of Truth.) For my
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52640:6"/>part I ſhould, and I think you ought, above all things, to dread Popularity, and to be moſt afraid, when you ſee men, many men, your People and Hearers, to take and drink all down, examining nothing; and all this only out of the good opinion they have of you their Teachers, though others in the mean time, and for the ſame matter deride and ſcorn you. Oh! how happy would it be if men, Chriſtian men, would once come to this excellent Spirit <hi>(i. e.)</hi> To conſider and judge of things, of all things, even things of Religion, as they are in themſelves, in their own nature; and ſo receive and imbrace them, and be able, either to receive or reject, out of a free judgment: And neither to accept things for the ſake of men, and that good opinion they have of them, nor to reject any thing, becauſe they like not the men, that write or ſpeak it, or becauſe they are not of their Party or Opinion: Till this be, Chriſtians will never excel, nor be wiſe unto Salvation, nor credit Religion. I confeſs the men that object this againſt you, to your reproach, are moſt unfit to do it; partly</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> For that ill temper of Spirit in which they do it; it ſeems to be neither out of Piety, nor Charity, nor out of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to do you any good, or in any thing to amend you; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides many of them are (I ſay not all) plainly men of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly ſpirit, ſo far from taking that way of Charity, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Simplicity, which the Goſpel of our Lord requires, that they put all their truſt, of overcoming their adverſaries, in their prophane Jeſting, Joaking, turning Religion into ridicule, Deriding, Jeering, Scoffing at all men of a contrary Party, without making a difference, handling the matter in difference, in a Prophane, Poetical, Comical ſtrain and drollery, and not after that ſerious manner, and with that deep ſenſe, nor with that Charity, which thoſe things require; ſo that their writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and talk of this kind, ſuites more to the Play-houſe, than to the Church, not caring what they ſay, ſo they can either find, or create matters to diſgrace their Adverſaries with.</p>
               <p>This Jocular ſtrain of theirs, with a pleaſure in handling matters, and anſwers in the like kind, ſeems to have taken too much hold on ſome of you, in the imitation of them, to the no little diſgrace and diſcredit of the moſt holy, and pure Truth, and ſimplicity of Jeſus.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:52640:6"/>Some of you, alſo delight too much to pleaſe the People, and tickle their Ears with ſuch like ſtuff, with Jeſting and Joaking at your oppoſites, with girds and ſarcaſtical hints againſt them, telling your familiars, with too much delight their faults, and not ſeriouſly, nor charitably pitying them, nor wiſhing their good and betterment. Thus if we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them; you incourage and maintain others, to draw the Saw of contention, and to carry on the Cauſe in difference at ſuch a rate; which if you better conſider of it, appears not to be Chriſtian, nor will you find peace in it at laſt; it no way agreeing with the gravity and ſeriouſneſs of a Chriſtian, nor with the dread and weighty concerns of Religion and mens Salvation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Another account upon which I judge them very unfit to object againſt, or retort upon you: Is firſt, becauſe I find ſome of the main matters, they make faulty, and draw particular abſurdities from, in your Prayers and Preaching, in ſome opinions, are common to themſelves with you: Such I find to be the opinions and differences about the five contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted points, concerning Election and Reprobation: What they will needs call <hi>Calviniſm,</hi> you call the contrary <hi>Arminia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm.</hi> The conſequence and matters drawn from thoſe, they ſtill make matters of ſcorn, and wherewith to expoſe you, as is plain and manifeſt, in moſt of their late Writings and Books, eſpecially thoſe made by their Divines.</p>
               <p>They take in the worſt, and moſt obnoxious parts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences, of your opinions (though there be both Godly and Learned men on both ſides) on purpoſe, thinking thereby to diſgrace the Non-conforming Brethren, which is a moſt diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous way of proceeding.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Becauſe thoſe notions and opinions, (called <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianiſm</hi> and <hi>Contra-Remonſtrant,</hi>) are the plain ſenſe of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> (or elſe we have loſt all our ſenſes, and all men elſe as well as we) till ſome few of late will needs fancy otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Becauſe there are ſtill many, and have been more in times paſt, of the moſt Learned, if not the moſt Pious and Zealous of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that have imbraced, held,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52640:7"/>and ſtrenuouſly defended thoſe opinions: Now to ſcrew abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities out of theſe notions and opinions, to take hold on theſe ungrateful things, and the conſequences of them, that are moſt obnoxious to cavil and cenſure; when in the mean time the beſt and ableſt of their own Party, are of the ſame mind, and have ſpoken the ſame things, and full as abſurd (if they will have it ſo) as any; as it were eaſie to point to Books, and Authors of this kind: I ſay, to do this upon theſe terms, is moſt diſingenuous, and unworthy men and Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>Finally, They are moſt diſingenuous and unworthy in this their procedure, in their Cavils, and Accuſations of Abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, and Phanaticiſms in Preaching and Praying, charged upon the Nonconformiſts; ſeeing it were an eaſie work to do the ſame by them, if any were ſo minded, and could not better ſpend their time, or could adventure to waſt their Conſcience, and expoſe Religion to ſcorn upon ſuch a ſcore. There are thoſe that think they could do it, and ſome in times paſt that have done it, and find matters enough, and too much for it; but enough of this, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore, ſeeing they are ſo troubleſome and offenſive to you in this kind, I truſt you will not be Imitators of them in the ſame way of working; deriding, ſcoffing and expoſing them, for their faults, errors and miſcarriages. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſome will plead on both ſides, that inſtance of <hi>Elias</hi> in mocking <hi>Baal</hi>'s Prieſts, to countenance all the Mockery, Drollery and Scoffing, made uſe of in Religion, and about Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious matters, and Religious men. To which I ſay,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let not us Chriſtians look upon the ſingle practice of any, no not of the beſt men in Scripture Records; but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they agree with and ſavour of, the Spirit of Holineſs, Peace and Charity, acting in the Goſpel of Chriſt, and will conſiſt with the promotion of the high and holy end and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of it; that is, according to the Life and example of our Lord Jeſus, who hath taught us the moſt excellent things, and given us the worthieſt examples of them, in all peace, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, meekneſs, goodneſs, charity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Again, if a wiſe man ſhould for once be found in ſuch a way, or do ſuch a thing, <hi>i. e.</hi> deride, mock, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52640:7"/>would be enough to do it once, but to continue in it, and ſtill to anſwer the adverſary, as faſt as he doth it; is not only un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of a good Chriſtian, but of a ſober wiſe man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solomon</hi> has an excellent ſaying to this purpoſe, <hi>Anſwer a fool,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>according to his folly, leſt he be wiſe in his own conceit, i. e.</hi> For once perhaps thou mayeſt ſometime do ſo, and but once, as the following words imply, <hi>Anſwer not a fool according to his folly, leſt thou be like unto him, i. e.</hi> By continuing to anſwer him ſtill according to his folly, as long as he ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt therein, thou ſhalt be like unto him, a fool alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As 'tis not fit for Chriſtians to return Railing for Railing, ſo neither Scoffing nor Joaking, for any thing of the ſame kind.</p>
               <p>Yet this has been done, if they ſay true, not without the Knowledge, Agency, Incouragement of ſome of your way, who have ſate too much in the ſeat of ſcorners, <hi>(viz.)</hi> in ſmart Sarcaſms, prophane Poetry, and in Pictures, Draughts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to render the contrary party ridiculous and abſurd as much as they can, all which falls under the divine prohibition againſt prophane jeſting, ſcoffing, reproaching, and villifying, and breeds very ill conſequents and effects, <hi>(viz.)</hi> anger, malice, hatred, revenge, making of Parties, diviſions, deſtroying of Chriſtian Peace and Charity.</p>
               <p>We ſhould conſider, every man hath ſome honour and vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for himſelf, for his Friend, and for his Party; and few can bear to have this Crown ſpoiled, to be degraded from their honour, or have their name and reputation laid waſt; but will above all things, be ſtirred and provoked by ſuch dealing and detraction. Conſider with your ſelves, if it be not ſo with you; Sure I am, this way of proceeding is moſt Unchriſtian, and agrees not at all with that good Spirit which is peaceable, full of love, tenderneſs, fear, humility, and which becomes and recommends the Chriſtian Goſpel of our Lord and Saviour: Neither is it agreeable to the Royal Rule, of doing to others, as we would be done unto our ſelves.</p>
               <p>Finally, ſome good and godly men, I have known, that have ſomewhat tranſgreſſed this way; and though upon the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt provocation given, and that repeated and publick; yet thoſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52640:8"/>humble and holy men have repented of it, and publickly, and in Print, retracted it. In a word, you as Chriſtians ought not to follow any in this kind, but to give examples to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <p>FUrther, There is one thing, and the principal thing, you are charged with, (which I doubt is to too true, at leaſt hath more of truth than I could wiſh) and that is a too much buſying your ſelves about publick and State-matters, and things relating to Government; and conſequently too much, and too great a buſying your ſelves, in hearing and telling News, ſpending much time about it in Publick-houſes and elſewhere; and that too much of your Hearts and Spirits are drunk up about ſuch matters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is offenſive and hateful to the contrary Party, ſcandalous to your Profeſſion; and doubtleſs a great hindrance, to other more ſerious and neceſſary work; and in ſome even to the forgetting and neglecting the weighty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of their own Souls, and eternal happineſs; if not to the neglect of their Places and Callings, their Time, the order of their Families, and duties in their Relations; I condemn none in particular, but in the general. A cry and noiſe there is abroad of ſpending time this way, and good Chriſtians have obſerved, that they have never known any overmuch given to hear, or take up and tell News and Stories of all kinds, and about State-matters in ſpecial; but they have obſerved a great decay in their Spirits, and found them growing to a great degree unſavoury, loſing much of that good ſavour and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, that they had in time paſt. And ſo becoming much the worſe in the temper of their Spirits, and it is to be feared in their uſefulneſs in their Places.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But you will ſay; What may we not concern our ſelves in the affairs and paſſages of the Times we live in? Muſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52640:8"/>we not ſerve our Generation the beſt we can? And if ſo, how can this be without obſerving and ſpeaking about the matters and tranſactions herein? Beſides, are we not Parts and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Nation and Kingdom we are born in; and have a right, yea a Birthright to all the legal Rights and Priviledges of it; and when we ſee theſe invaded, may we not mind it and ſpeak of it? Muſt we ſee Popery, Arbitrary Government, coming on apace upon us; and not take notice of it, nor obſerve and ſpeak of it? Are not our Lives, Liberties and Poſterities concerned in theſe things? and have not there been Helliſh Popiſh Plots ſet on foot, and continued againſt us? To be ſure we ſhall ſuffer with the firſt and the deepeſt, and ſure all this is enough to ſtir us and concern us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Anſwer, <hi>(Firſt)</hi> No doubt but Chriſtians may concern themſelves in the State, and Affairs of the places where they live; but this is to be done in fitting ways, without ſcandal, or being over-buſie, or juſtly ſuſpected of any undue deſign and practice.</p>
               <p>(And I who know ſomething of the Diſſenting Party) do believe they have none to carry on: Nay, I find them every day more and more, (ſo far as I know them) inclining to Peace, Patient, ready to bear all that comes, or is threatned to be laid upon them: Though it has not been without cauſe of jealouſy, that ſome were willing enough to provoke, and would have been glad to ſee them provoked, to ſome undue courſes and diſturbances; that ſo they might have had occaſion to have perfected and crowned their Plot! But thanks be to God they were deceived!</p>
               <p>But I was ſaying, that doubtleſs you and all Chriſtians may concern themſelves in ways Chriſtian, and proper to them in the Afairs of Government and State, in the place where they live. And that,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> In their Prayers, for the good of it, directing them to God, ſuitable to the occaſions or workings of the deſigns on foot, in the preſent State, and Kingdom, and Government they live under.</p>
               <p>We are commanded to make Prayers, Supplications, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſions, giving of Thanks for all men; for Kings, and for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52640:9"/>all men in Authority; for this end, that under them we may live a quiet, peaceable life, in all godlineſs and honeſty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And of old the People of God were commanded to ſeek and to Pray for the good and peace of the place where they lived, though it were in Captivity: <hi>For in it they ſhould have Peace,</hi> Jerem. 29.7, 8.</p>
               <p>And ſo we may and ſhould obſerve, what motions and matters are carrying on in the Land and Government; that we may direct our Prayers accordingly, with fit and ſuitable argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments unto God, for the good and the peace of it: That is the firſt thing, they may and ought to do.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> If need be, and matters go againſt us, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to our minds, (and as we think) not as they ſhould; we may certainly with humility, petition and pray unto men and thoſe in Power; and expreſs our ſenſe and fears about things, pray for what we deſire in a peaceable way. None ſure can be againſt this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> But if the motions and deſigns we fear, and like not, be not our concern, as we are of ſuch a Party, diſtinct from the reſt; but do concern the whole body of the Nation as well as us. There is no reaſon we ſhould ſeem more afraid, than the reſt; but be able (ſurely) to bear as long as the reſt of the Nation doth, ſo long as ſuch deſigns are not evidently deſtructive to the whole: Neighbours fare here, if it be not the beſt; yet it may at preſent ſatisfie us, to take our ſhare in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. If they will bear it, or not mind it, ſhall we only, or firſt, or moſt, concern our ſelves more than others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Much leſs ſhould we be the forwardeſt in matters of this nature; and it is worſt of all, and altogether unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable to be querulous, ſtill thinking and cenſuring the worſt of things; to be diſcontented and find fault, to be found more forward to take exceptions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We ought, having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved how things are, let them appear never ſo ill; yet to do in this, as in other things, we are commanded; in nothing to be careful, but to commit our ſelves and requeſts to God by ſupplication, and to receive the good we have with Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving; and the God of peace, and the peace of God, will keep and guard your minds in peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:52640:9"/>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> For you to meddle and concern your ſelves over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſily, will be worſt taken of any; it will be ſcandalous, and of ill reſentment above all others. You are at ſome difference with them on the account of Religion, and are Diſſenters from the National eſtabliſhed Worſhip, and therefore ſhould meddle the leſs, and the leaſt of any, in publick State-matters and differences, unleſs called to it.</p>
               <p>I wonder, but cannot tell how it came to paſs, that in our late Differences and Controverſies, in State and Civil matters, you ſhould then be, or how now you come to be reckoned as a Party in the preſent Difference as well as the other; ſure I am it ſhould not be ſo. What! becauſe we are Diſſenters in ſome matters relating to Religion and Worſhip; muſt we needs be ſo too in other matters of State and Government? As I ſaid before, we ſhould be ſo much the leſs in theſe, and indeed ſcarce ſeen in them: It is moſt unhappy to be thus involved; and if it be the ill deſign of any to have it ſo, or to repreſent you as ſuch, we ſhould ſtill ſo much the more decline it.</p>
               <p>You ſhould remember how apt the World has been in all Ages to caſt the crime or ſuſpition, at leaſt of Sedition and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion upon the Diſſenting Party; ſo it was objected againſt the Chriſtians, when the world was <hi>Pagan,</hi> &amp;c. So when it was <hi>Popiſh;</hi> and ſo it hath always been, and is like to be. And at this preſent, common Fame, the common Pamphlets, and Prints will needs proclaim; that ye are Diſſenters from, and oppoſite to the Civil as well as Religious eſtabliſhment. Though it may not be uncharitably ſuſpected and conjectured, that they which charge you moſt with Sedition and Rebellion, would be moſt glad, if they could have the opportunity to ſee you ſo, and find you actually ingaged therein; and that it would both pleaſe them, and advance their deſign for the total ſuppreſſion of you; but I truſt that they ſhall for ever loſe their longing. However, ſtill the reaſon and argument of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion to take you off, from minding and meddling too much in thoſe concerns, is ſo much the more forceable and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive upon this ſuppoſition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> When ever any have (through the force and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of violence, perſecution, hard and cruel uſage) been
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52640:10"/>forced out of their patience, into paſſion and diſcontent, and ſo into Inſurrection, Rebellion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for their defence: The ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary has improved this, either to the utter deſtruction and extirpation of them in thoſe places where it has been, or at leaſt to make their States and Caſes, much worſe than they were before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Indeed it has ſeldom, or ſcarce ever been ſeen, that God has bleſs'd this way of Chriſtians going about to better and amend themſelves, <hi>i. e.</hi> The way of force, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could it be expected, it being quite out of Gods way, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Spirit and way of Chriſt Jeſus; and to that pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, meekneſs, bearing of Injuries, Oppreſſions, Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with a patient continuance in well doing and well-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, according to the example of our dear Lord: Truſting in the living God, committing our ways unto him, waiting patiently upon him, till he in his own due time (which is the beſt time) help and deliver; which if he ſhould not do in this World, is not the hope of that to come, ſufficient to enable Chriſtian men to bear and ſuffer here for a little ſeaſon? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly if Chriſtianity be true, and truly believed; it is enough that it promiſes ſo great a good to thoſe, who continue in ſo good and approved a way.</p>
               <p>However, upon the whole you may ſee 'tis not ſafe med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dling, yea ſcarce ſafe ſpeaking of State and publick matters and differences, except ye ſpeak on the prevailing ſide, which if you can't do, it is beſt, moſt prudent, and ſafeſt, not to ſpeak at all, others may do it better than you; and you ſhould be the laſt, if at all concerned in thoſe matters; eſpecially as you are private men, and Chriſtians, not called to any place of Councel, or advice in theſe matters. And if it be not, ſcarce at any time ſafe, and ſeldom Chriſtian, and right to meddle in publick affairs in a way of oppoſition; how ill then and unjuſtifiable are they that make ſuch things the matter of, or at leaſt bring them into their Prayers, Sermons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and by that means both ſin againſt God, their Neighbours, their Rulers, and expoſe themſelves, and all that are reckoned of the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Party to hatred, if not to deſtruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:52640:10"/>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Further conſider, that as the Kingdom of Chriſt is not of this World, ſo neither are you, that are his ſubjects, to be much concerned about it; nor to reckon, or account, of any great matter for your ſelves in it. The Saints of God of old did, as we are now commanded to do, and have greater rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it than they, <hi>(viz.) To be as ſtrangers and pilgrims in this preſent World: And to paſs the time of our ſojourning here in fear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have work enough to do, and time little enough to do it in; to work out our ſalvation, to diſcharge the work and duty we have to do as men and Chriſtians, in our Places, Standings and Relations, to give a good account to God of our coming in, and continuing for a while in this World; to mind the great deſign and purpoſe of Chriſt, and his coming into the World, which all that would be accounted his Servants and Subjects in his Kingdom, are bound to mind, <hi>i. e.</hi> How to ſave our ſelves and others, and by all good example and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, to draw men from off their ſins, unto God, unto righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and holy living, that they may eſcape the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that is haſting apace againſt all ſinners unrepentant; and to endeavour this way to encreaſe the number of Chriſts ſubjects and followers; this bleſſed deſign will find us and you all work enough. I wonder much, that among all your talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about News and Stories, Matters and Affairs that are work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; that you do not mind thoſe things more, and why they are not the ſubject matter of your Diſcourſe, as often as you can, that all may ſee to whom you do belong, and according to whoſe Spirit and Principle you are led; and may ſee, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed you have been with Jeſus, and learned ſomewhat of his Spirit.</p>
               <p>I know no concerns we have to buſy our ſelves meerly as Chriſtians, and meddle in matters of State-affairs now, more than the Chriſtians of old had, that lived under the Heathen Emperors, or they who now live under other Princes, that are of a different Religion; the Ancient Chriſtians were right glad if they could be but quiet in their Religion and Profeſſion, being in that Diſſenters from the State they lived in; and could they enjoy peace and liberty this way, they ſeemed to be pleaſed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52640:11"/>well enough. For indeed ſurely the Chriſtian Religion was never much favoured, where it was profeſſed in the purity, ſimplicity, and excellent liberty of it; nor for ought we can know, ever will be by the power and greatneſs of this World; and when ever they have gone about to help it, by the addition of their Power and Authority, and with the aſſiſtance of State Intereſt and Policy, it hath ſcarce ever, or ſeldom thrived, or been encreaſed thereby.</p>
               <p>We know, and 'tis upon record, how excellently this holy Religion and Profeſſion of Chriſt Jeſus did thrive and grow, when the greatneſs and powers of this World; yea, of all the World, were againſt it, when it ſtood upon its own Legs; went forth conquering and to conquer, in its own power, and having no carnal, but ſpiritual weapons, to aſſiſt it and fight for it, even ſuch as it had in it ſelf, and in its own nature: The Divine power, (ſecretly) but moſt effectually wrought in it. Oh! the excellency of the Divine Power of this excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Religion, called Chriſtian, if it were left to its ſelf, and to the conduct of the great Author of it, by his Spirit that is promiſed to attend it, both in its progreſs in the World, and in the hearts of men. Since the Powers of this World, would needs extend their favours to it, and exert their force in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of it, and not letting it proceed, upon its own Principles, but adding to it the Intereſt and Policy of State: Oh! how feeble is it grown, it can make no ſuch progreſs in the World as it did; but hath loſt much ground, of what it had, as is plain in many, and eſpecially in the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Parts of the World and elſewhere.</p>
               <p>So my Chriſtian Friends and Brethren, ſhould it be as to your way or profeſſion; if it be of God, and of the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit with the Doctrine of Chriſt, to which it pretends, it will be enough to live of it ſelf, without any dependance on the State where you live, and make profeſſion of it; and it would encreaſe and enlarge too, if men lived up to it, and managed it according to that Spirit of holineſs and heavenly vertue, that it teaches; ſo that you need not concern your ſelves, leſt you ſhould loſe your Liberty, your Religion, your Poſterity be over-run with Popery and Tyranny; and great fears
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52640:11"/>in this kind are ſometimes more than there is cauſe for. How many have ſadly and fooliſhly troubled themſelves, lived in fear of Popery, Plots, Maſſacres all their days, ſpoiled their own peace, and have died a thouſand deaths, before they needed? It is ſufficient to die once, and not to live in a conſtant fear of it, which is worſe than death.</p>
               <p>(In a word) If you and all ſuch had minded their own bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, been earneſt to work out their ſalvations, had let their light ſhine before men, in all peace and patience, goodneſs and beneficialneſs to all doing all good, and bearing all evil, ye would have found, that your own, and the publick good and welfare, had been better provided for, and you had done more to promote the Kingdom and Glory of Chriſt in the World, and better ſecured the peace, liberty and quiet, both of your ſelves and poſterity, than now by all your ſtrivings, motions and concerns in State Affairs and matters relating thereunto. This is the wiſdom that is from above, that is firſt pure, then peaceable; that by patient continuing in well doing, obtains all good, overcomes all evil, ſecures the main of all unto us, both in this World and in the World to come, (Godlineſs hath the promiſe of both.) To which the Lord Jeſus conduct us all in ſafety, granting to us to walk in this way unto happineſs, and in no other, to think to find it. <hi>O Lord let thy Kingdom thus come,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Whereas it is confidently pleaded that you have a right, and Birthright to all Priviledges of the Nation, and the Kingdom you live in, and in which you were born; and that therefore you ſhould concern your ſelves as you do. I Anſwer,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> And Pray you, however (as hath been ſaid) that if you do it, it may be according to your Places and Callings, peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably without ſcandal, ſo as not to be juſtly accounted buſy or pragmatical, nor to contradict any of thoſe holy Chriſtian Rules, that are ſuperior to all Civil rights whatſoever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> I Anſwer, If the Laws be hard againſt you, how can that be help'd, or how can you ſtruggle againſt it, ſeeing it is your own principle; that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Laws do ſecure the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Rights: And that the people are to be both governed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52640:12"/>and judged, according to the declared Laws of the Land. So that ſtill ye ought to be quiet and ſilent.</p>
               <p>But you ſay your Civil Rights are invaded; whether you ſay true in this, or whether they on the contrary, muſt be left to be judged of by the general judgment of the Nation in the great Councel of it; but for private perſons to contend much about theſe things, ſeems to make matters but the worſe, and to prejudice others the more, becauſe you do ſo much, and ſpeak ſo much about them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> (And laſtly) you are to conſider, that according to the Chriſtian Doctrine and Principles, you are ſometimes to forego, and not reckon of, nor regard, neither your Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral nor Civil Rights and Priviledges; you may inſiſt upon, and plead them when they may do you good and ſervice, as <hi>Paul</hi> did his <hi>Roman</hi> Freedom: But to make matter of needleſs quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel and conteſt, and great concern, and ſo to cauſe diſturbance, or unquietneſs, or ſcandal about them, I know no warrant you have; but that for the Goſpel-ſake, and for peace-ſake, and the healing of prejudice, you ought to let them alone, as if they were not.</p>
               <p>For conſider, are not the peace and enjoyment of our Lives, Goods, Eſtates your Natural and Civil Rights? yet are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians upon occaſion to part with all of them? to looſe and ſay down their Lives, to ſuffer joyfully the ſpoiling of their Goods, where they can't ſave them without ſin, and ſcandal, or breach of their Faith as it is in Jeſus?</p>
               <p>Again, it is ſo far from being a Truth at all times, and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable, that Chriſtian men ſhould ſtand ſo ſtiff upon their Rights, Birth-rights, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or whatever elſe is due to them, that not only to avoid ſcandal they are to wave and ſuſpend them.</p>
               <p>But further, (though there be no reaſon from without forcing them) They ſhould and muſt ſometimes voluntarily forego their Rights, and lay all aſide for the Truths ſake, and other good Chriſtian purpoſes, when they can by ſo doing promote peace and godlineſs in the World, and encreaſe the honour and credit of the Goſpel thereby. Thus the Apoſtle, though it was his right to take Money, or reward for his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52640:12"/>Preaching, and he proved it by many Arguments ſo to be; yet he wholly waved it when he ſaw that the taking of it would prejudice, and the waving of it would promote the Truth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some will conceit, that to forego theſe things for Chriſt ſake, <hi>i. e.</hi> for his Honour and Intereſt in the World, is not ſuffering for Chriſt, except we bear a Teſtimony to his Truth in the way of Martyrdom, or ſuffer Perſecution for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Truth. But they ſhould conſider, that there is a ſuffering for Chriſt and the Goſpel, though it be not in the way of Perſecution nor under tryals of that kind; when for his ſake and Intereſt, and carrying on the Affairs of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in the World, we deny our ſelves of any of our profits, rights and priviledges, and do not inſiſt upon them, nor ſtand to maintain them, when and though they are due unto us <hi>E. G.</hi> all juſt debts are our right and property, and ſo may we ſeek and ſue for them (as 'tis generally ſuppoſed and preſumed) in a legal way; yet when this by ſome intervening circumſtance, may become ſcandalous, or not falling in with the main de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; we may not in ſuch a way, ſeek our own, and ſo in many other things, and in this thing now in queſtion.</p>
               <p>Finally, ſome will plead, that though we may give away our own Right, yet we can't anothers, nor the Right of our Poſterity. But to this I ſay,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That I am not about to perſwade you to give them away, but not always to inſiſt upon them, at leaſt not ſo much, and before things of greater moment to you than they.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> You need not to forego the Right of them, nor yet be ſo buſy, and concern your ſelves ſo much about them. A mans Eſtate, and Life is and may be his Poſterities, yet may he lawfully if need be, ſell the one, and lay down the other, and part with both for the Goſpels ſake.</p>
               <p>More might be ſaid, but I wiſh that thoſe things were better minded and underſtood, that we might have juſt knowledge, and true notions of the true Goſpel Principles, and the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:52640:13"/>
               <head>SECT. IV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> ANother matter, many of you are much ſuſpected of by your Friends, and ſometimes poſſibly charged with by your Enemies, is a formal profeſſion in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; boaſting, or at leaſt judging your ſelves Saints, the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial peculiar People of God, his elect and choſen, over-valuing your ſelves, and over-looking and deſpiſing others (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if not of your own way and Party) and this only for your profeſſion and ſeparation-ſake: And that though you pretend more in this kind, and greater purity than others; yet you ſhew forth no more of real vertue, nor of the unqueſtionable fruits of well-doing than others, that pretend not ſo much; and they think, becauſe they can't ſee more, that there is no more goodneſs or betterneſs in you, than in others; but only that you pretend to be more ſeparate, and worſhip after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner, than they do: All which they think is but hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and fancy, and that as every one will have their way, ſo you will have yours. They think that it is now, as it was in Chriſts time, and that this generation is but like that, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That one ſort or part of the Nation (which you call pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, carnal and wicked) are as the Publicans, open ſinners and harlots. The other, as the Scribes and Phariſees, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hypocrites, though they pretended more, and ſeemed better, indeed were worſe and harder to be convinced and amended than the others.</p>
               <p>Now conſider Chriſtian Friends and Brethren, whether you or ſome of you, if not many of you, have not given too much occaſion for this judgment and ſence of you, (among the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar) by your manner of walking, and the temper of your Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; whilſt as to real goodneſs, and righteouſneſs, and better<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, above and beyond others, they can ſee no difference, or but little: This you ſhould conſider, and mind to convince you what you ought to be, whatſoever they think of you.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:52640:13"/>Conſider firſt, That the Chriſtian Religion according to the mind of the great Author of it, and his intent and deſign in it, hath this main and principal purpoſe to be carried on.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> The amendment, and betterment of men, in their Souls and Spirits, that they may be regenerate, inwardly and really changed from evil, or a ſtate and condition of evil unto good; have the Divine Nature wrought in them, which is diverſly deſcribed and ſet forth in the Scriptures of the New Teſtament. You may take it in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Commiſſion, in which he gives account of what he was to do, by vertue of it, <hi>Acts</hi> 26. v. 18. i. e. <hi>To turn men from darkneſs to light, from the power of Satan unto God, that they might receive forgiveneſs of ſins; and Inheritance among them that are ſanctified,</hi> by the Faith of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Or we may take it in ſhort, as our Lord expreſſes it, <hi>(viz.) To make the tree good, i. e.</hi> The man, the Chriſtian man, to have a Divine living principle of goodneſs in himſelf.</p>
               <p>The next part of this bleſſed deſign follows upon the other, <hi>i. e.</hi> the bringing forth good fruits, that the goodneſs or ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Tree, (or Chriſtian man ſignified by it) may be known to himſelf and others, by his fruits. Now the fruits by which alone, we or others, can rightly judge, are not of that ſort of duties that conſiſt in outward profeſſion, and performance of outward Ordinances, Praying, Hearing, Preaching, or doing ſuch kind of works, but in the doing of others, better than thoſe, and demonſtrating our true Faith in Chriſt. So Chriſt our great Prophet teaches, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 21. <hi>Not every one that ſaith, Lord, Lord, i. e.</hi> That calls on the Name of Chriſt, and makes Profeſſion of him; yea, that doth this with great zeal, for that's the meaning, as appears in the doubling of his Title, (Lord, Lord.) All that do thus, ſeem they, or be they never ſo zealous in it, ſhall not therefore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Kingdom of Heaven. But ſaith our Lord, <hi>He that doth the will of my Father which is in Heaven, i. e.</hi> He that actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and really does it, in the moſt ſubſtantial parts of it; which is not done by only calling upon his Name, but in other more excellent works and fruits, beyond this, of a Profeſſion of, and calling upon him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:52640:14"/>And in the 22. <hi>v.</hi> To enforce this, he tells us of a ſort of men owning this way and Religion, and doing many great and wonderful works, upon the account of it, who were confident in themſelves of being right and accepted. Yea, it ſeems, they lived and died, and roſe again in this confidence, becauſe they had Prayed, Propheſied, Preached, in the Name of Chriſt, were great doers in, and frequenters of Religious exerciſes; and moreover wrought great works, caſt out Devils in Chriſts Name, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet all this would not do. In the 29. <hi>v. They muſt depart into everlaſting fire. Mat:</hi> 25. Chriſt knows them not, they were workers of Iniquity, and it is not likely that they were open ſinners, openly prophane, or like the <hi>Publicans,</hi> &amp;c. For then they could not have had ſuch confidence.</p>
               <p>But thus it was, they either had reſerved to themſelves ſome ſecret ſin, indulged themſelves in ſome corruption or particular evil; or elſe they had not done that good, nor brought forth thoſe fruits, which they ought to have done for the glory of God, and to anſwer thoſe great obligations of holineſs, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and Divine purity and rectitude which the Goſpel and bleſſed Religion of Chriſt Jeſus had laid upon them. And now this matter being weighty and conſiderable, and ſeeing men are like to deceive themſelves by a zealous Profeſſion, without real goodneſs and good fruits, to demonſtrate it; Therefore our Lord further preſseth and enforceth this matter, from <hi>v.</hi> 24. to the end, by a Parable of two men that built Houſes upon diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent foundations; one upon the Rock and the other upon the Sand; the one was wiſe, the other fooliſh: The application ſhews, that let men pretend what they will, nothing elſe but the doing of the real indiſputable will of God will ſtand them in ſtead, and make them able to ſtand and weather it out to the laſt. Read the place and conſider it well.</p>
               <p>Now according to this bleſſed deſign of the holy Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus, which is we ſee to make men good. And next to manifeſt this by good works, and abounding in them, in ſuch good works and fruits, that both good and bad men can judge of, which they can't do by all your great profeſſions, and outward Religious performances.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:52640:14"/>According to this, I ſay, conſider and judge of your ſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> As to the temper of your Spirits, to ſee if the Tree be good. You ſeperate from common ſins, and corrupt worſhip; then ye ought in all things elſe to be uniform in your Lives and Spirits.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Are ye more patient, meek, humble than others?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Are ye more mortified to this preſent World, or do ye make it evident that ye are more moderate in the things of it than others; and doth your moderation in this appear unto all men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Have you mortified your corruptions and inordinate affections, ſuch as anger, wrath, pride, hatred, malice, evil-ſpeaking?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Are ye more courteous, condeſcentious, kind, affable, gentle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Read that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 22. what the true fruits of the Spirit are, you ſhall find them there ſpecified, <hi>(viz.) Long-ſuffering, goodneſs, gentleneſs, faith, meekneſs, temperance.</hi> And if you mind the place, you ſhall find the fruits, called the fruits of the Spirit, here mentioned, to be ſuch that are ſhewed towards, and made manifeſt to others, And for the good and benefit of others <hi>E. G.</hi> the Love, there ſpoken of, is not love to our ſelves, but to others, or the loving of others: So Joy there mentioned, is joy or rejoycing in the good of others; for it is no great vertue to joy in our ſelves, or to rejoyce becauſe of our own happineſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So Peace, another fruit, is to be peaceable with all men, long-ſuffering, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſuffering long, or bearing with other men, though never ſo great enemies to us; or long-ſuffering, in bearing all the injuries men can heap upon us: And alſo long-ſuffering, in bearing with, and waiting long upon men, with much patience, for their good, and to do them good, and to take them off from their evil ways.</p>
               <p>To this is added Gentlenenſs; and to all Goodneſs, <hi>i. e.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficialneſs, or a being beneficial, and profitable to men. The Apoſtle <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. will give us a full account of a good man, what he is, and how diſtinguiſhed from a righteous or a juſt man, by which we may know, what goodneſs is here, and what he means there.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:52640:15"/>Another fruit is Faith, <hi>i. e.</hi> Fidelity or faithfulneſs, for ſo ſometimes the word is uſed, and muſt be here ſo taken: We are to be true and truſty in all things, faithful to our words and promiſes, and in things committed to our charge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, meekneſs, temperance and vertues of that kind, againſt which there is no Law, nor exception, but they are approved, commended by all, both good and bad. Theſe fruits thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, are the moſt proper fruits of the Spirit, and are of the true Spirit, and temper of our Lord Jeſus who ſhewed himſelf thus towards all men. Theſe will make us moſt like our Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father, and are moſt evidently demonſtrative of the truth and reality of our faith in Chriſt, by theſe we glorify God; ſuch a temper of Spirit as this we muſt deſign, and muſt be growing in it; for we are not like to be compleat at firſt. And ſo it is <hi>v.</hi> 24. <hi>They that are Chriſt's, have crucified, or mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, the Deeds of the fleſh, with the affections, luſts,</hi> or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, <hi>of it, i. e.</hi> They have done it, or at leaſt, muſt be in a way of doing it, growing in it and getting the victory over thoſe luſts: This is to be ſo done and proceeded in, that the power of Chriſts death may be ſeen in the death of our ſins and carnal affections: And the power and force of his reſurrection in our riſing daily to newneſs of life, and works ſuitable.</p>
               <p>And <hi>ver.</hi> 25. <hi>If we live, i. e.</hi> If we profeſs and pretend to live <hi>in the Spirit,</hi> or according to the power of the Divine life. Then <hi>let us alſo walk in,</hi> or according to <hi>the Spirit,</hi> as it is here deſcribed in the fruits of it: And let us judge our ſelves, and let others judge of us, no otherwiſe, but according as they ſee us thus walk, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But on the contrary; are ye not often charged, and do ye not give too much occaſion for it, with divers things contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to this <hi>E. G.</hi> with anger and wrath, with being ſubject too much to humour and fancy, rather then led by the ſober prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Reaſon and Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> according to the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, calm, and meek Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> With being too much guilty of Covetouſneſs, Earthly-mindedneſs, and of too much following of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent World; and ſo not ſhewing forth ſuch freeneſs, ſuch a liberal Spirit as the Chriſtian Goſpel teaches, and gives ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52640:15"/>of: This being in the nature of it, moſt oppoſite to a narrow contracted ſtingy mind and ſpirit; this teaches to be free, liberal, bountiful, all which much grace Religion, and the profeſſion of it. Conſider how greatly this excellent ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and bountiful temper, in all ways of Charitable dealing and Hoſpitality credits all Religion, even a falſe one: And it is ſo natural to the Spirit and Principles of the Chriſtian Religion, that if the practice of it were more, it would infinitely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote and propogate it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> You are ſuſpected and charged with being too much conformed to this World; and ſome of you, as much as any, <hi>(viz.)</hi> In pride, vanity, gallantry, in your Selves, Clothes, Habits, and in the Education and bringing up of your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in ſcandalous ways and breeding, according to the Pride, Pomps and Vanities of this World. Some that have looked into your Ways and Garbs, yea into your Meetings, Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, have ſeen as much of this as any where elſe. And if they have a mind to ſee more, they may go from thence to the Dancing Schools, to the moſt pompous and vicious parts of them, your Balls, Maſques, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By occaſion of all which, ſome ſcoff, others take offence, others are grieved, and ſome take occaſion to go into the contrary extreams, ſeeing ſo much pride and vanity, in and among Profeſſors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That you are often found Oppreſſors, Hard, if not ſometimes Cruel; will take the utmoſt advantage you can, will not relieve when need and equity requires; but will (like other men, or the worſt of men) tye up all to their Bargains, Contracts, though there be never ſo great reaſon to conſider them: You as well as others, have been cryed out upon, on this account; one inſtance was in the Letting of Houſes and Leaſes, at, and ſince the late Dreadful Fire, and Rebuilding of the City. Some have wrought upon mens Neceſſities, taken advantage of their weakneſs, want of skill and cunning to look well to themſelves; and when any have found it, and complained of it, not the leaſt help and relief in it. This dealing hath been charged upon ſome great Profeſſors, and pretenders to Religion, and ſeemingly devout. You would do well to mind and conſider, how far you may have been guilty
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52640:16"/>of this, and take the judgment of others, and of indifferent perſons in the Caſe. Some are complained of, as being of an Oppreſſive Spirit, in Trading, Dealings, Bargains, Payments, eſpecially by the poor Tradeſmen, and the Labourers that Work and Sell to you, and perhaps dare not complain to you, nor contradict you, for fear of offending you; you never learned this of Chriſtianity, nor of Chriſt Jeſus the Author of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That when you are Injured and Angered, you can't freely forgive, nor bear much; but are too apt to envy, hate, take the rigour of the Law; theſe and ſuch like matters are objected againſt you, or divers of you, and none can deny, but many have given too much occaſion for it. The truth is, that an excellent Bountiful, Charitable Religion, together with the great work of Self denyal, and of Patience, Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and the Mortifying of the luſts, paſſions, and evil affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the fleſh, is a Religion quite out of faſhion, and by many diſgraced and diſparaged, as only a piece of dull mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: Chriſtian men make no work, nor deſign, to excel in theſe Vertues, though it be the only excellent way, to glorify God our Heavenly Father, as our Lord teaches, <hi>Let your Light</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>i. e.</hi> your good works, <hi>ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee them, and thereby glorify God, your Heavenly Father.</hi> No other way without this, no other way but this, will do it. Nothing but the doing and abounding in ſuch works, and in ſuch an excellent temper of Spirit, as we learn from Chriſt Jeſus; and a principle in our ſelves from which ſuch works flow. Such fruits and works by which we can glorify God, are thoſe, and of that kind, which the moſt Looſe, Carnal, Atheiſtical men can judge of, as well as others; they can tell, as well as any, who is moſt Meek, Humble, Patient, Innocent, Harmleſs; who is moſt Charitable, Bountiful, Beneficial; who moſt Courteous, Affable, Gentle, Condeſcentious; who is moſt Faithful, Careful, Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, uſeful in the Places, Callings, Relations, God hath ſet them in: They can tell, who moſt abounds in Pity, Mercy, Compaſſion and Clemency, and who are moſt free from Pride, and Paſſion; who are Ill-natur'd, Ill-humour'd; who moſt Sweet and Obliging: In word, who it is that carryes on a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52640:16"/>deſign of Religion and Godlineſs. Theſe things, they are (at leaſt, to ſome good degree) capable to diſcern, diſtinguiſh and judge of. But for mens Opinions, Sects and Parties, differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in Religion, and things of that kind; theſe they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not, neither do they value nor eſteem them, nor think any great matter, of the zeal of men, of different Parties, about ſuch things. They underſtand them not, and think that all is but Humour, Fancy, Superſtition or Hypocriſy; and that as all men will have their way, and humour in ſome things or other, ſo in Religion too. But they can tell who doth the moſt good, and who can, and will bear the moſt and the greateſt evil, with patience, without ſeeking Revenge, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning like for like. It is this and theſe unqueſtionable, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſputable works of righteouſneſs and goodneſs, that will draw men to the love of God, and Religion, and the ways of God, when they ſhall ſee men ſhew forth the vertues of God. Theſe works will put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men; theſe alone will (if any thing will) work upon men, for to bring them, to the love, and obedience of the Goſpel of Chriſt. The Scriptures of the <hi>New Teflament,</hi> and that lately cited <hi>Mat.</hi> the <hi>5th.</hi> and others do teach us, that this way of well doing, is the laſt and the moſt powerful Argument, and of greateſt force, to win men over to Chriſt Jeſus. So that a great truſt is left and committed to all the owners and profeſſors of Chriſtianity, that they ſee to the propogating of the Goſpel, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating of the will and purpoſe of God in it by well doing. The deſign and purpoſe of this holy Religion, is the ſalvation of a ſinful World; the Word of God, is indeed, open and plain before the evil World; they may look into it, their conſcience can't but ſometimes ſmite them, for the neglect of their duty: But this they ſearch not into, it is not ſo open and plain to them, does not make ſuch impreſſions upon them, as when a draught of Religion is drawn, in the holy Lives and ways of Chriſtian men, and ſo preſented unto them: 'Till this be done, no great matter will be done in the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let the <hi>5th.</hi> of <hi>Matt.</hi> eſpecially from <hi>verſe</hi> the 38. to the end, be heedfully and carefully read and conſidered to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. And add to this the <hi>6th.</hi> of <hi>Luke</hi> from the <hi>7th.</hi> to the 36 <hi>verſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:52640:17"/>
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <p>THere are ſome other things, taken notice of in you, though not ſo much as in ſome others; yet too much, and too much cauſe there is for it; one inſtance, and the main one is in a matter which it is confeſs'd many others are guilty of beſides you: And that is, that you (many of you) make the condition of your Chriſtian and Church-Communion, ſo narrow, that none can be admitted into it but juſt your ſelves, and thoſe of your own Party, or particular Opinion, who in every thing are juſt of your mind to a tittle; ſo that if other Chriſtians differ never ſo little from you, either in Doctrine or way of Worſhip, nay perhaps ſometimes but in a Ceremony, (though otherwiſe good Chriſtians and Holy men, giving good proof, ſhewing forth good fruits, of the truth of their Faith in Chriſt Jeſus) yet are, notwithſtanding, for the want of, or defect in, ſome ſmall matter, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> rejected as much as the verieſt Heathens and Publicans; ye will have no fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip or communion with them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> To inſtance in (a thing that concerns ſome of you) the ſubject of Baptiſm (which though of all things leaſt deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving) hath made more noiſe and trouble in the Chriſtian World, than a thouſand more weighty matters: There are alſo many other things of like nature, or not much differing, that are made as much a bar and partition Wall, as the Jewiſh Ceremonies were of old; what they were between Jews and Heathens, theſe are made to be between Chriſtians and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, which is a matter moſt ſad and deplorable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> I confeſs, you have had examples and preſidents, without number, for this uncharitable practice; but it hath been from ſuch, ye have no cauſe to boaſt of, that they were your teachers and exemplars, in that you have rejected and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated from them upon this account; I mean the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, to go no further. They indeed, in all Ages ſince
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52640:17"/>they began to be triumphant in the World, have not only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded all other Chriſtians in the World, from their Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, becauſe of ſome differences and diſſentings from them, but as much as lay in their power uſed them worſe than Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, accuſing them for Hereticks, and denying the poſſibility of Salvation unto them. And thoſe that through impoſition and cruel uſage, they had thruſt out of their Communion, and forced to ſeparate, becauſe enjoyn'd to believe and practiſe, as the condition of their Communion, things which were plainly againſt their Light and Conſcience, and which they judged moſt contrary to the Word of God; they then followed with all manner of uncharitableneſs, and cruelty, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, as the vileſt and worſt of men, branding them, as He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks and Schiſmaticks; which if indeed they had been, yet they had no warrant, or a juſtifiable cauſe, to proſecute and perſecute them as they did; ſeeing neither they nor any elſe have more power, right or authority, over others to compel them to their way, than others have to compel them, if they had power in their hands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Now thoſe are the men, this is the Church that you have ſeperated from, for thoſe kind of practices; as you and a great many imitate and follow too much. Some of you, were you in a condition, and had power, would deſtroy all thoſe that differ from you; for if you exclude and ſhut out all from your Communion, becauſe of ſome difference in judgment, or opinion and ſome practices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it is no great unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſs, to think you would do more, if you had more power in your hands; and we not only ſuſpect it, but many of the more rigid ſort do not deny it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But not to charge you too deep, nor all for ſome, I do believe that many, and great numbers of you, mean no ſuch thing, as to hurt any diſſenting or differing Chriſtian, farther than to exclude and deny him your Church Communion, and ſo to let him ſhift as he can. But</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> What warrant have you to reject any that profeſſeth Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, and lives at leaſt as good and ſober a Life as thoſe that are actually of your Communion (his diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or diſſenting in ſome matters only excepted?) Either he muſt be rejected by you for every difference, or any diſſent
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52640:18"/>whatſoever, which I think none will ſay, except <hi>Papiſts:</hi> And they, though they ſay it, yet do not, cannot practiſe it; 'tis well known that they do tolerate great differences among themſelves, and that conſiderable Parties, and potent Orders of men, among them are at variance one with another in the ſame Church, <hi>E. G.</hi> about Predeſtination, the Immaculate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, and other things; nay, they are not well agreed about ſtating of their great Fundamental of the Churches In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility: The union that is among them, is rather politick than real; ſo that I may preſume ſome difference will be, ſome muſt be allowed, in the ſame Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Therefore when Communion will not be allowed upon the account of different apprehenſions in opinion and practices, it muſt be for ſome opinions and practices in ſpecial, ſuch as ſome men will call great and fundamental Errors, or as others call them, intolerable (for it ſeems they will make a difference between tolerable and intolerable) but it is manifeſt every Party of men, be there never ſo many, will have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing they call fundamental, proper to themſelves, and to their Party; and any that hold any thing in oppoſition to them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, muſt be accounted intolerable, not to be born and ſuffered in the Church; though otherwiſe never ſo good and uſeful. <hi>E. G.</hi> The <hi>Papiſts</hi> will account the Churches Infallibility, and ſome peculiar Doctrines, as Tranſubſtantiation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals. And ſo again among the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> ſome called <hi>Lutherans</hi> will (it's probable) account their Conſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Fundamental: And thoſe called <hi>Calviniſts</hi> will account the decree of abſolute Election and Reprobation, a Fundamental; And on the contrary part, ſome Remonſtrants or <hi>Arminians</hi> of the more rigid perſwaſion, may make their Opinion ſo funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental, that they will not have Communion, nor ſuch Charity to thoſe differing from them, as Chriſtian men ſhould have one to another, though erring, and perhaps ſometimes great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but yet as is to be hoped, meaning well. The rigid <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Presbyters</hi> will reckon their Model of Claſſical Church Government, by <hi>Presbytery,</hi> as good as a Fundamental, and all that will not ſubmit to it, are by them accounted perſons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable; nay, perhaps they will (for ſome ſuch like thing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52640:18"/>has been) riſe in Arms, kill and deſtroy, for the ſake and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of their Model of Government, preſuming it of Divine right, and therefore not ſuffering any other Form or Model, to ſtand with it or by it.</p>
               <p>Once more, Thoſe called <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> have not much come ſhort of making the Baptiſm they practiſe a Fundamental. For, <hi>Firſt,</hi> They have aſſerted and maintained it as of neceſſity to Church Communion; and to be ſure whoever were not Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized according to their way and mode, were not accounted capable of Chriſtian and Church Communion; and ſo by a near-hand inference, not of ſalvation; which ſome of the more rigid ſort have not been afraid to aſſert. All thoſe, and a thouſand more, may thuspretend, to make fundamentals, and the errors contrary to them intolerable: And ſurely many of them, have abſolutely denyed Chriſtian Communion to all that could not come up to their way. But thanks be to God, many of thoſe are commendably enlarged, as to this matter, and will now allow a Latitude, that before they would not; I pray God to enlarge them, and all good Chriſtians beſides, ſtill more and more.</p>
               <p>But you ſee here are many fundamentals; and none knows how many more men may make, according to the humour ignorance or Intereſt of their Party; and what one ſort calls fundamental Verities, another will be as forward to call funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Errors, Hereſies and Wickedneſſes. What courſe can we now take, but to love and receive all Chriſtians as ſuch, as Chriſtians that believe in, and love Chriſt Jeſus, and do not contradict this by any wicked works, or ill living, contrary to it?</p>
               <p>But you will ſay, What is there nothing fundamental, in the Chriſtian Religion; no rule to proceed by in judging who is fit, for Chriſtian and Church Communion, and who not? muſt any one that calls himſelf a Chriſtian be allowed to be ſo, and admitted to all Chriſtian Communion and Church Priviledges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I anſwer:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> There is no Sect or Party of Chriſtians, can aſſign a rule to judge by, as they are ſuch a Sect and Party; nor can tell us of any Fundamental which another Party or Sect, will not contradict, and aſſign ſome other perhaps contrary to it, and hold that for fundamental, or a matter of neceſſity; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52640:19"/>to which only, they will take and receive men into their Communion. So in the firſt place, we muſt not look to any one Sect, or Party, for a Fundamental, or fundamental rule to judge, of the capacity of perſons, for Chriſtian and Church Communion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is a Fundamental, proper to Chriſtianity as ſuch, that all Chriſtians do acknowledge: And what is this? but the owning and profeſſing of this one thing (which is both a fundamental and firſt principle in Chriſtianity) that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus is the Chriſt, or the Chriſt of God; take it in the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. where he faith, <hi>The word is nigh thee verſe</hi> the <hi>8th.</hi> what word? even this; That Jeſus, is the Chriſt, owned of God, approved by him, and that in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial manner teſtified by the Reſurrection from the Dead; whom God would never have raiſed, if he had not been the Lord Chriſt; the place runs thus, <hi>The word is nigh thee, even in thy mouth, and in thy heart, i. e.</hi> The word which we preach, which is, <hi>If thou ſhalt confeſs with thy mouth the Lord Jeſus, and ſhalt believe in thy heart, that God hath raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſhort, the confeſſion and open owning of Chriſt Jeſus is a Fundamental, and neceſſary to ſalvation; and whoever doth this, ſhall be ſaved; and therefore ſhould be received and accepted as a Diſciple of Chriſt, being thereby made capable of Church Communion, and Priviledges of that kind. This is the Fundamental, no other foundation can any man lay, or make, but this, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. <hi>ver.</hi> And as it is a great funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental verity, that whoſoever believes ſhall be ſaved; ſo that he that confeſſes or profeſſes this, ought to be by all accepted and received as a Chriſtian, and treated accordingly; is ſo plainly laid down in the Scriptures, that it is a wonder, that either Ignorance, Intereſt, Partiality, or Uncharitableneſs, ſhould ever have the confidence to riſe up againſt it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Scriptures are many, and ſo plain, and perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous, that they are every where to be found; ſo many that it is a tedious labour to cite them all; ſee but a few.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> When Chriſt himſelf and his Apoſtles firſt Preached, there was no more required to make a Diſciple than this Faith; when the Apoſtles Preached, after his reſurrection, it
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52640:19"/>was the ſame, and no more was required but to believe, and profeſs or confeſs, that Jeſus was the Chriſt; and then, in thoſe firſt times, as a preſent ſign that this was their Faith; and to oblige themſelves to this Jeſus, and his Doctrine and Laws, they were Baptized, and ſo admitted into the neareſt and cloſeſt fellowſhip, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. and <hi>verſe</hi> 41, 42. <hi>Then they that gladly received his word, were Baptized. And the ſame day there were added, about three thouſand ſouls. And they continued ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly in the Apoſtles Doctrine and fellowſhip, and in breaking of Bread, and in Prayers.</hi> Nothing more was required of them, to inſtate them into all the Chriſtian Rights and Priviledges; and being admitted into the Church, they were to be further educated and inſtructed by the converſe and ſociety they had there; that they might grow up to perfect men in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and be made fit for every good work.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Thoſe three thouſand converted to Chriſt, in ſo ſhort a time, could know little of Chriſtianity, or the Laws and deſigns thereof; they did only acknowledge that Jeſus was the Chriſt, whom they received and accepted of, for their Lord and Saviour. Yet this was a ſure way, to put all, (not only) into a ſavable ſtate, but into all the rights and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, belonging thereunto. So moreover, when <hi>Peter, Mat.</hi> 16. made ſuch a frank Confeſſion of his Faith, this very Faith we ſpeak of, <hi>That Jeſus was the Chriſt, the Son of the living God;</hi> Immediately a bleſſing, or a bleſſed priviledge was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon him; (as it follows there) and accordingly all Chriſtians are indued with the ſame, upon their believing, and open confeſſion, and profeſſion of the Name of Jeſus. Therefore, all thoſe little conditions, and qualifications, that men now make, and require of Chriſtians before they will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them, into the Chriſtian Church, and Fellowſhip or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints; are Conditions and Orders their of own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing, and ſerve only to form a Party for their own purpoſe, (as all Sects have commonly ſomewhat peculiar;) more than to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance Religion or Godlineſs; and of this kind are all other Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions laid upon men, as the condition of their admiſſion into the Church. Some have of late days deviſed, and practiſed, that men muſt make a confeſſion of their Faith, in a great
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52640:20"/>many Articles, or according to ſuch and ſuch Creeds, that be in faſhion among them, and muſt believe juſt as they do; which a man may do, or however, may profeſs to do, and yet be as bad, as unregenerate, carnal, and hypocritical as the worſt. Some others, before they will admit any into their Church and Communion, will exact a Formal Narration, or Declaration, not only of their Faith, but of their Converſion, and the work of Grace upon them, with the manner of their Converſion and Conviction, at their firſt turning from their ſins to God; but there's no certainty in this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> For oftentimes, thoſe that are moſt conſident, and bold, can do this, when others of better Spirits, and better in the main, can't; nay, it is to be feared, many may ſtrain here to ſay more than is true, or more than they have had the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Others, ſometimes have related ſuch paſſages, and circumſtances in reference to this matter, which were but tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial, abſurd, if not ridiculous.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Suppoſe ſome to have had real Convictions, and trouble of mind at ſuch a time: Have not many had Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that yet have not proceeded to a real and through Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and a change of heart, and ſpirit? And have not ſome been changed or converted, rather from one ſin to another, from ſins more carnal, to ſins more ſpiritual, than from ſin it ſelf, wholly unto righteouſneſs? I ſay not of any, that they are ſo, but 'tis poſſible in ſuch a way, men may deceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and others, ſo no certainty of knowledge, by ſuch a Confeſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> But however it is, they to whom this Confeſſion, or Declaration is made, are as wiſe as they were before; and can paſs but little better judgment, than they could at firſt; becauſe proceeding by no certain rules, but thoſe of fancy and conceit, and the opinion they have of the preſent capacity, and honeſty of the perſon, ſpeaking or declaring; if he be either ignorant, ſtrongly conceited or hypocritical, he may deceive them all.</p>
               <p>Much more might be ſaid againſt this new way, and theſe new deviſed conditions and qualifications; and to ſhew that all
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52640:20"/>are to be received, who profeſs Faith in Chriſt, and promiſe to walk holily and obediently, according to his Laws, to the beſt of their knowledge and ability; if afterwards they appear to be, or walk otherwiſe, they are to be looked unto, watch'd over, admoniſhed, reproved, and in caſe of non-repentance, or not amendment, to be ſeparated, cut off, and withdrawn from.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> And finally, (as to this) to add this word more. The caſe may be, that many that are of upright hearts, and truly fearing God, who have from the heart turned unto him, and hate all ſin, as ſuch, and are truly humbled for it; yet are able to tell neither time, nor circumſtances in particular, when or how this change was made and wrought in them.</p>
               <p>Such a work may grow by degrees by vertuous Education or otherwiſe: The beginning of the power of the Kingdom of God in the heart, may be like that (as to its progreſs) which our Lord ſpeaks of, of the Kingdom of God. The good ſeed of the word, (according to the ſimilitude of the Corn ſown in the earth) the blade firſt appears, then the ear, then the full Corn in the ear: no man preſently perceives himſelf, much leſs another, to grow; yet he may ſee that he hath grown, and is growing in the power of the Divine Life, and in good time, it may become manifeſt in him, by the fruits of it, both within and without: He may be born of the Spirit, that knows not the time, nor particular way how this did operate in him. But to conclude, what if it be real, that ſuch perſons do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and acknowledge, and that they were really changed from evil to good; yet there is no reaſon, neceſſarily to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that therefore they muſt be ſo ſtill.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Another Argument as to this, is taken from the nature of the Chriſtian Religion, which being the laſt, and ſo the moſt liberal and extenſive of all the revelations and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſations of the counſels of God, unto the World, for the better progreſs, and propogation of it; it is in the nature of it made fit for the whole World, and the ſtate of all mankind. And therefore, according to the nature of it, and intendment of God in it, muſt needs allow a great Latitude, to the ſeveral ways, cuſtoms, uſages, of men in their ſeveral Nations, and States: Every Nation and People, has ſomewhat peculiar, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52640:21"/>particular, and differing one from another, according to which the Chriſtian Law and Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus, will ſuit, in a good degree; ſo they be not ſinful in themſelves, nor contrary to the main holy end and purpoſes of this Religion; yea ſo free and large is this Chriſtian diſpenſation, in the nature and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of it, that as it will yield much to the ſeveral ways, ſo to the weakneſſes, radicated opinions, cuſtoms, humours of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral particular perſons, at leaſt for a time, until they have learned, or grown to better knowledge and maturity: Thus it is in its ſelf, and thus it was at firſt, when firſt preached to men, and propagated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Inſomuch that, that excellent ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous ſpirited perſon, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> in conformity to the free nature of the Goſpel, did become all things to all men, in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.19, 20, 23. <hi>verſes, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the</hi> Jews, ſaith he, <hi>I became as a</hi> Jew, <hi>i. e.</hi> In many things complyed with the <hi>Jews,</hi> in their Laws, Cuſtoms, Ceremonies, the better to win them off from thoſe things; again, <hi>As without Law to them that are without the Law, i. e.</hi> Without the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Law, (or perhaps any poſitive Law) for he ſpeaks of the converted Gentiles, who though under the Law of Chriſt, did yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain many of thoſe Ways and Cuſtoms, unto which they had been accuſtomed, whilſt <hi>Gentiles;</hi> that he <hi>might gain them that were without the Law, i. e.</hi> gain them by degrees quite over to the compleat true Goſpel, Liberty and Sanctity, which at firſt, and all at once could not be done; ſo <hi>ver.</hi> 22. He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed with the weakneſſes and humours of ſome men, not yet well grown, <hi>i. e.</hi> (as himſelf ſaith) He <hi>became all things to all men, that by all means</hi> (ſuch means of complyance) he <hi>might gain ſome,</hi> which he could not poſſibly, nor lawfully do, if the Goſpel, or Chriſtian Religion, were not of ſo large and liberal a nature, as to allow it: Therefore it is, that this Goſpel is much celebrated for its great liberty, and men are warned and cautioned they ſhould not abuſe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Thus it was not under the Law, that would not bow, nor bend it ſelf, no not in little things; they were ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enjoyned according to the letter of them, and ſo it might better be then, conſidering that, that Diſpenſation and Law, in the nature of it, was ſuited, fitted, and moſtly limited to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52640:21"/>that People <hi>(Iſra l)</hi> and the ſtate of things, as then they were: The Worſhip was limited to one place, the Prieſthood to one Family; all that were admitted to officiate in Sacred things, to one Tribe; with many other Reſtrictionis, Limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, Commands, Promiſes, Threatnings, which made it peculiar to them, and to that time, for it was but for a time being ſo confin'd, and made ſo narrow in the Laws and Terms of its Union and Communion, that Proſelytes could never be admitted to the full of the Rights and Priviledges of it, with the natural <hi>Iſraelites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this Law was removed, for the comparative unuſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and unprofitableneſs of it, ſeeing it would not fit all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, or men as ſuch; Therefore ſeeing God intends to reveal his Name, and Mind, unto all, and to bring all into one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fellowſhip, both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles;</hi> this former Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation and Law muſt needs be removed, and another more liberal yielding, and extenſive, come in the room of it; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially as to things, that ſome call indifferent, things not evil in themſelves, but leſs neceſſary; that way might be made to come at all, if they agreed in the Main, <hi>i. e.</hi> in the Belief, and Acknowledgment of Jeſus the Chriſt of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is not here to be underſtood, that the Chriſtian Goſpel doth yield in any of its eſſential Principles, or that it doth proſtitute it ſelf to any of the ſinful ways and luſts of men, or comply with them in the lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>: But only that it doth not command nor injoyn any thing, as neceſſary in its ſelf, or unto Salvation, but what in its own nature is ſo; and if men be made holy, and are ſanctified in their ſpirits and inward man, fruitful in their Lives in all well-doing to the glory of God; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially if abounding in Love and Charity unto men, it will make them allowance otherwiſe, as to the ways and cuſtoms of Men and Nations. This then being the Nature and divine Conſtitution thereof, nothing is more unreaſonable, and more contrary to it, to the deſign and ſpirit of it; than impoſition of the Cuſtoms and Ceremonies of one Nation, or of one Church upon another, or of any number of Chriſtians upon other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; and (that which is the main Matter I now mind) the denial of Chriſtian fellowſhip and Communion in the Church,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:52640:22"/>or in any the Eccleſiaſtical Priviledges of it, upon any account of difference in Opinion and Practice on this ſide the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Nothing that I know can debar any, except the Name of Jeſus and Chriſtianity be denyed, or not acknowledged; or that they live unworthy of their Profeſſion. They that hold the Truth in Unrighteouſneſs, Ungodlineſs, Uncharitableneſs, though they do not deny Chriſt and his Goſpel in words, yet in works they do, which is worſe, and a great diſgrace unto it; from ſuch we are bid to ſeparate our ſelves. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>v</hi> 5. but we muſt not ſeparate for things, wherein good and ſober Chriſtians may differ; as ſome particular Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and Practices, or Modes of Worſhip; unleſs thoſe things be impoſed, as neceſſary to Salvation, or made the Condition of Communion; or that we are not ſuffered to enter our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, in matters wherein we do diſſent; which liberty ought always to be allowed, that it being known how far we do agree, we may ſo far walk together. And for Differences in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar points, and ſome Ordinances, and Practices, if in theſe we be otherwiſe minded, as we may be, God in the way of Peace, and of a ſincere Enquiry, will in due time reveal it unto us, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 15.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> For further Proof, at leaſt, for our further ſerious Conſideration of the Divine Nature, and liberty of this bleſſed Religion, called Chriſtian, that it does give ſuch a Latitude, ſuppoſing we hold to the Main: See a few Scriptures to this purpoſe, from that bleſſed and induſtrious Apoſtle, who beſt knew and underſtood, the nature and extent of this gracious Diſpenſation of God in Chriſt, for the uniting and bringing all together in one. <hi>i. e.</hi> in Chriſt Jeſus, notwithſtanding many and various differences otherwiſe. <hi>Rom. chap.</hi> 2. he diſputes at large againſt thoſe that truſted and had confidence they ſhould be accepted, and pleaſe God, becauſe they were ſtrict in the obſervation of the Law, as to Ceremonies, and the ritual parts of it, though failing in more weighty things; and proves, That God will not accept any, but upon the account of that real in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent Righteouſneſs, which conſiſts in the real fruits of well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, <hi>v.</hi> 25. <hi>For Circumciſion verily profiteth, if thou keep the Law; but if thou be a breaker of the Law, thy Circumciſion is made <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion,</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:52640:22"/>or nothing. He tells them, that there may be ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit in Circumciſion (Circumciſion is here put (as part for the whole) for the Law-ſervice) this may profit you if ye keep the Law.</p>
               <p>The Law is taken here emphatically, for the moſt ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial part, or great things of the Law, which the Scripture and right Reaſon ſtill diſtinguiſh, by way of dignity and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy from the Ceremonious part, and Church Priviledges, and performance of outward Ordinances.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle here ſpeaks of real Godlineſs, Mercy, Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Purity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which being in us, there may be ſome profit in the other to us, but not without theſe.</p>
               <p>Therefore <hi>verſe</hi> 26. <hi>If the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion, i. e.</hi> an uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed Perſon, <hi>keep the righteouſneſs of the Law, i. e.</hi> in the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial and neceſſary parts of it, <hi>Shall not his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion, be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted for Circumciſion? i. e.</hi> he ſhall be as well accepted of, as if he were actually circumciſed, or had really kept the whole Law, in the ritual and Ceremonious parts of it, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Law of Ordinances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Though he have kept and obſerved none of theſe at all, yet keeping the other which is the Main, he ſhall be accounted of, as well as the Circumciſed.</p>
               <p>See more to the ſame purpoſe in <hi>verſe</hi> 27. he roundly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes: And <hi>ſhall not the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion, i. e.</hi> the Perſon uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed; <hi>if it fulfil the Law, judge thee, who by the Letter and Circumciſion doſt tranſgreſs the Law?</hi> And verſe 28, 29. <hi>But he is a Jew.</hi> So we may ſay (upon the ſame principle of reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) he is a Chriſtian, not which is one outwardly, or is bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized only outwardly, but he is a Chriſtian indeed, that is one inwardly, and Baptiſm, <hi>is that of the Heart, in the Spirit, and not ſo much in the Letter,</hi> or in literal Baptiſm, <hi>whoſe praiſe</hi> on this account, <hi>is not of men, but of God.</hi> So the concluſion, for our purpoſe is fair, <hi>(viz)</hi> that though a man ſhould not be baptized at all, with outward, or water Baptiſm, but ſhould ſcruple that, or the time of it, or the ſubject of it, yet if he be, and can be judged to be, a true Chriſtian by his acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of Chriſt, and purpoſing, or promiſing, to walk in his way, it is enough, as to God's acceptance; (and it is ſtrange it ſhould not be ſo to men) and conſequently, the Chriſtian
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52640:23"/>Religion doth allow a free Communion to all, differing in all ſuch like things. I would have all that read this, to mind it, and to look upon the Scriptures before them, to ſee what a little matter they make of thoſe differences about Ordinances and Ceremonies, which may, or may not be uſed and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, without ſcruple or trouble among Chriſtians; and learn to eſtimate men, not for ſuch things as theſe, but for their real worth and uſefulneſs.</p>
               <p>To this add <hi>chap.</hi> 14. of this Epiſtle, where we find Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans differing about keeping of Days, and about Meats; ſome making Conſcience of keeping ſome Days more than others, ſo of Meats, making a difference and Conſcience of eating ſome, not others. <hi>verſe</hi> 2, 5. <hi>One eſteems one day above another, another eſteemeth every day alike.</hi> What does the Apoſtle now? does he perſwade the one to come over to the other? No ſuch matter, but what does he do to end the Controverſie? Even this, exhorts that one ſhould bear with, and not judge and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure another. See the whole <hi>Chap.</hi> for this, and conſider it well, with the Apoſtles manner of reaſoning in it; he accounts that every one of them may mean well, and ſerve God in his way.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 6. <hi>He that regards a day, regardeth it unto the Lord. He that regards not a day, to the Lord he doth not regard it, i. e.</hi> 'tis for the Lord's ſake, he hath no regard to it. <hi>He that eateth, eateth to the Lord, and he gives God thanks. And he that eateth not, to the Lord he eateth not, and he giveth God thanks;</hi> both give God thanks, both think they ſerve and pleaſe him, and therefore in the mean time, ſhould live at peace one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and all others with them.</p>
               <p>But further, What are now the common Principles, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they ſhould agree, and keep and maintain Love, and Charity, and Chriſtian Communion together? Not at all theſe things in Queſtion among them, but the Apoſtle lays them down in <hi>verſe</hi> 17. <hi>For the Kingdom of God is not,</hi> ſtands not <hi>in meats and drinks,</hi> days and times, or in the obſervation of things of this nature, wherein men are at liberty; but it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts <hi>in Righteouſneſs;</hi> we are to underſtand, that Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs before deſcribed, that is diſtinguiſhed from thoſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:52640:23"/>things in difference, Righteouſneſs in the moſt excellent ſence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He adds, <hi>and in peace, i. e.</hi> peace and quietneſs one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, notwithſtanding ſuch differences; <hi>and joy in the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> or joy in the Holy Spirit, <hi>i. e.</hi> rejoycing in that common Intereſt, and Spirit they all have that are in Chriſt Jeſus, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made like unto him, of the ſame Spirit and heavenly Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with him, which is wrought in them, by the holy Spirit; they ſhould rejoyce and love one another, becauſe they all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the ſame bleſſed divine Nature and Spirit; And up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this account alſo, (and upon no other) have their Names written in the Book of Life.</p>
               <p>It follows, <hi>verſe</hi> 18. <hi>For he that in theſe things ſerveth Chriſt, i. e.</hi> (to make the Apoſtles Argument compleat and pertinent) though he wants or differs in other things: yet <hi>is acceptable to God, and approved of men, i. e.</hi> He ought to be approved of men, and is approved by all wiſe men, and underſtanding Chriſtians, as to all Chriſtian purpoſes and ſervices other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. He proceeds in his Argument, and the uſe of it, <hi>ver.</hi> 19. <hi>Let us therefore follow after the things, which make for peace, i. e.</hi> better things than thoſe, about which you contend, and which <hi>may edifie,</hi> or things wherewith one builds (as the word ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies) another in all Chriſtian Faith and Vertue.</p>
               <p>In 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.19. <hi>Circumciſion is nothing, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion is nothing;</hi> (what then?) <hi>but the keeping the Commandments of God,</hi> &amp;c. But were not Circumciſion, and other Ordinances which are ſignified, under, or by this, the Commandments of God? They were ſo; but in compariſon of, and coming in competition with the great things of the Law, they were in ſuch compariſon no Commandments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and as to the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this ſaying and aſſertion; Chriſtian men are here by the Apoſtle commanded to keep their Places, fulfil their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants and Contracts, doing ſervice to them, with whom they have covenanted, to be Servants; all which was of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter uſe and neceſſity, and of more honour to the Goſpel, than to ſtand upon ſuch kind of things, as Circumciſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> his drift may be ſeen from the <hi>17th,</hi> to the <hi>24th, verſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:52640:24"/>Another Scripture is <hi>Col.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 11. <hi>In whom alſo ye are circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, with the Circumciſion made without hands, in putting off the body of the ſins of the Fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. The Apoſtle here to take them off from admiring and making too much of outward Circumciſion, (and there is the ſame Reaſon of outward Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm) tells them, there was no great need of it, ſo they had the inward Circumciſion, the inward Baptiſm. <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>They are buried with him in Baptiſm, i. e.</hi> Spiritually, but really bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed into his death, according to the ſence and meaning of <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>Therefore we are buried with him, in,</hi> or by <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> into death; <hi>that like as Chriſt was raiſed up from the dead by the glory of the Father, even ſo we alſo ſhould walk in newneſs of Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The burying here, is of the ſame nature and kind with the riſing again, as is more plain, <hi>v.</hi> 13. <hi>And you being dead in your ſins, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion of your Fleſh, hath he quickened together with him,</hi> &amp;c. And though this place, and ſome others are not brought abſolutely to exclude a Literal, or Water-bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm to them that think themſelves under the Obligation of it; yet it is the Spiritual and Myſtical Baptiſm, that is princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally meant, and doth principally, if not only, ſuit and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate the Apoſtles Intent and Argument here, which is to take men off from putting too much truſt in, and laying too much ſtreſs upon the outward Circumciſion or Baptiſm, or other things of like nature. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5, 6. <hi>For in Chriſt Jeſus, i. e.</hi> in the Religion and way of Chriſt Jeſus, or of the Goſpel of Jeſus, <hi>&amp;c. Neither Circumciſion availeth any thing, i. e.</hi> no out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward performance or Ordinances of the Law; for Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as was noted, is put for the whole of the ſervice of that kind, <hi>neither <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion,</hi> that availeth not neither, <hi>i. e.</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be circumciſed, or to obſerve the literal Ordinances of Chriſtianity, availeth not much; what then does? but, ſaith he, <hi>Faith,</hi> Faith in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>that works,</hi> operates <hi>by Love,</hi> or Charity, Chriſtian Charity.</p>
               <p>Add to this once more, <hi>chap.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>For in Chriſt Jeſus, neither Circumciſion availeth any thing, nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion, but,</hi> (what does avail?) <hi>a new Creature,</hi> a new regenerate ſtate, of which we may ſee more in 2 <hi>Cor. chap.</hi> 5. from <hi>v.</hi> 14. to <hi>v.</hi> 18.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:52640:24"/>So that nothing avails according to the Apoſtle here, and to right Reaſon it ſelf, but that which is ſubſtantially good; a real change of the Heart and the Soul of a Chriſtian, from ſin unto God. And at <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>And as many as walk according to this Rule,</hi> or if any man walk according to this Rule, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſtand not much upon ſuch outward Rites and Ceremonies, but mind the Main, the new Creature-ſtate, the divine Nature, and eſtimate and value themſelves, and others only, upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, <hi>Peace be on them, and Mercy, and upon the Iſrael of God, i. e.</hi> For or becauſe, ſuch are indeed the true Iſrael of God, and none elſe, and are to be treated accordingly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. the laſt the whole <hi>verſe</hi> ſtands thus, <hi>And as many as walk according to this Rule, peace be on them, and mercy, and upon the Iſrael of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. And take notice, that the Apoſtles purpoſe here, upon the occaſion there given, was to convince the Judaizing Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, of the no neceſſity of their ſtrict adherence to thoſe Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Ceremonious things; and that it was a fault ſo to do, and upon the ſame Reaſon; and to make his Argument con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding, we muſt take in the Chriſtian Rites and Ordinances, that are of an external and ritual nature, ſuch as Baptiſm, the Lord's Supper, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not that the doing or performing of thoſe things is to be condemned; no, they may be uſed, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the practice of almoſt all Chriſtians are uſed, and ſome ſpecial Reaſons may be given for their uſe, but we ought to eſtimate, perform, and uſe them with Subordination and Subſerviency to Peace, Charity, Edification, Godlineſs, and not otherwiſe; and if theſe ſhould (as 'tis poſſible they may) interfere with, and lye croſs to thoſe great and undiſputable things, they are rather to be left undone, than to make a breach upon thoſe other. The Apoſtles argument is built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this general Principle, that things of an inferior nature, as all external Ordinances are, ſhould give way to greater things when they come in competition; ſuch as Chriſtian Charity, Peace, Edification, Growth and Encreaſe in Chriſtian Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. His Argument reaches the one, as well as the other, and 'tis rational, ſo to underſtand it, and to make ſuch a differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between things and things of this Nature.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:52640:25"/>6. Finally, once more conſider, That the whole Epiſtle of this Apoſtle to the <hi>Ephiſians,</hi> is written to this purpoſe, to praiſe, admire, and magnify the grace of God, in procuring, and bringing about by Jeſus Chriſt, that there ſhould be a Coalition, or gathering together into one, of all People, Tongues, and Nations, both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles, into one, i. e.</hi> into Chriſt Jeſus, into the intereſt and way of Chriſt Jeſus; ſee <hi>chap.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 9, 10. <hi>Having made known to us the Myſtery of his will, according to his good pleaſure, which he had purpoſed in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that in the Diſpenſation of the fulneſs of times, he might ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together in one, all things in Chriſt; both which are in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and which are on Earth, even in him.</hi> And after he had magnified and admired this bleſſed divine Projection and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, in that <hi>Chap.</hi> and prayed heartily, that they might un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, and their Intereſt in it, being themſelves Gentiles to whom he wrote; thankful he is for this high grace of God, in Chriſt at large; and in ſpecial, minds them of the benefit by it, the exceeding good received by means of it, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they had been; in <hi>chap.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 11. <hi>Wherefore remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that ye being in time paſt Gentiles,</hi> at v. 12. <hi>That at that time ye were without Chriſt, being Aliens and Strangers, having no hope without God in the World.</hi> So at v. 13. <hi>But now in Chriſt Jeſus, ye who were ſometimes far of, are made nigh by the Blood of Chriſt,</hi> and ſo he proceeds to the end; and further amply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies this great grace, and their great honour in it, at v. 16. <hi>(viz.) That he might reconcile both unto God. i. e.</hi> Jews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, all mankind, which the Law could never do. This was the deſign. (Which though not known in other ages) yet now was manifeſt, as he thus expreſſeth it, <hi>chap.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>That the Gentiles ſhould be Fellow-Heirs, and of the ſame Body, partakers of his Promiſe in Chriſt by the Goſpel.</hi> And further, he ſhews, that it was a great Honour to himſelf, that he was made a Miniſter, and Preacher of this Grace. <hi>v.</hi> 7.8. <hi>Whereof I was made a Miniſter, according to the gift of the grace of God.</hi> v. 8. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto me who am leſs than the leaſt of all Saints is this grace given, that I ſhould preach unto the Gentiles the unſearchable Riches of Chriſt,</hi> with much more to the ſame purpoſe, in <hi>v.</hi> 9. <hi>To make all men ſee, what is the Fellowſhip of the Myſtery, which from the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:52640:25"/>beginning of the World, hath been hid in God.</hi> And <hi>chap.</hi> 2. He in particular deſcribes the way, how Chriſt did this, to bring them all into one Fellowſhip and Communion, <hi>v.</hi> 13, 14, 15. <hi>verſe</hi> 13. <hi>But now in Chriſt Jeſus, ye who were ſometimes far of, are made nigh, by the Blood of Chriſt.</hi> v. 14. <hi>For he is our peace, who hath made both one, and hath broken down the middle wall of partition between us, having aboliſhed in his Fleſh, the enmity, even the Law of Commandments contained in Ordinances, for to make in himſelf of twain, one new man; ſo making peace, and that he might reconcile both to God in one body by the Croſs, having ſlain the enmity thereby.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here we plainly ſee, all this was done, this Reconciliation between men and men was made, by the breaking down the partition Wall, that ſtood between Jews and Gentiles, which was the Law of Commandments, conſiſting in divers Rites and Ordinances, which whilſt they ſtood in force, this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral peace and good will among men could not be. The ſame matter does this Apoſtle teach in 2 <hi>Col.</hi> 14. compared with the <hi>16th,</hi> and <hi>17th, verſes,</hi> to which we refer you.</p>
               <p>Why now ſhall we our ſelves make partition Walls, between Chriſtians and Chriſtians, to keep them aſunder, and make them too of Rites and Ordinances, which Chriſt pulled down, took out of the way? Do we not ſee, that according to the deſign and intent of God, this bleſſed Goſpel is ſo conſtituted, that it might accommodate all, let them differ never ſo much, at leaſt, in thoſe kind of things, yea, and greater than thoſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Our buſineſs then is, to unite in Love, in Good-will, in Charity, in common Edification, and growth in Grace, and every Divine Vertue, and to take the joynt help and aſſiſtance of all, to carry on the great Goſpel work in the World.</p>
               <p>For want of this, theſe excellent purpoſes are ſpoiled, and we are in bad caſe, and the inſiſting too much upon theſe little things (for ſo they are even the beſt of them in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon) will naturally create a narrow contracted Spirit, and cauſe us to love and like none but our ſelves, and our own Party, not to take the help or benefit of any, but of our own Way and Opinion, and ſo every Party will ſtand for, and by themſelves; and mind only their own particular Sect or Church,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:52640:26"/>not the common good of the whole, or the Church Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick.</p>
               <p>O! Our God, amend this, and bring us all back from that Spirit, which is the Spirit of Anti-Chriſt, and moſt oppoſite unto the Spirit and Way of Jeſus Chriſt. To conclude,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Conſider, That the Goſpel is ſo conditioned, as to take in all, without the excluſion of any, upon any account, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept that of denying the Chriſtian Name, either in words, or manifeſtly in works, as hath been ſaid.</p>
               <p>And this the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 10, 11. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26, 27, 28. <hi>For ye are all the Children of God, by Faith in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, for as many of you as have been baptized, have put on Chriſt, There is neither Jew nor Greek, neither Bond nor Free; there is neither Male not Female, for you are all one in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> &amp;c. The Goſpel takes in all ſtates and conditions, into equal Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg, which the Law did not, and according to its Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, could not do. And touching differences in Judgment and Opinion, and ſome Practices, when all the Apoſtles, El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and Brethren were gathered together, in the <hi>15th.</hi> of <hi>Acts.</hi> Did they force or compel any? No, not ſo much as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, one ſide to come over to the other, but only at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to agree, leaving every one to their way, till time and growth in Knowledg, ſhould draw them nearer. And in the mean time, they were to keep peace and charity, and not be troubleſome one to another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And 'tis worth the while, to ſee the ground and reaſon, upon which they built that Union; none were to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled, or impoſed upon, though, or notwithſtanding, they did differ, but all be taken, and received into the bond of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Communion, as Chriſtians on this account, <hi>v.</hi> 8. That they had the Holy-ghoſt. <hi>i. e.</hi> many of them had, as well as the Apoſtles, and the elder Chriſtians at <hi>Jeruſalem, v.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>And God which knoweth the Hearts, bare them Witneſs,</hi> meaning, that they were accepted of him, and that he had teſtified it, by giving the Holy ghoſt unto them, even as he did unto the Apoſtles, and other Chriſtians. And <hi>v.</hi> 9. That is given for the principle Reaſon, upon which they were to be received, and nothing to be impoſed upon them <hi>(viz.)</hi> becauſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:52640:26"/>God had done the ſame for them; as he had for the reſt; which was, <hi>had purified their Hearts by Faith,</hi> and ſo no difference was to be put between the one and the other. This pleaſed all, reconciled all, nothing elſe would do it but this, and this will always do it, when Teſtimony may be had, that any are Chriſtians in good earneſt, imbracing the Name of Chriſt, walking according to the Law of Chriſt, in all the undiſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ways of Holineſs and Righteouſneſs, againſt which there is no Law, and about which there can be no Diſpute, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be good works, yea or no. To conclude,</p>
               <p>The ſum and ſubſtance of that Epiſtle ſent by the Apoſtles, and Elders, and the Brethren, ſet down, <hi>v.</hi> 29. that they, <hi>i. e.</hi> the new converted Gentiles, ſhould abſtain from ſome things there mentioned, was not impoſed or forced upon them; but thoſe things were recommended to them, and were things, not neceſſary (to be ſure) not all of them in themſelves, but for the preſent occaſion; and finally, if againſt all reaſon, it ſhould be ſuppoſed, that the Apoſtles, Elders, and Brethren, did here impoſe or command thoſe things, yet can no other, now or ſince, upon any reaſonable account, claim any ſuch Power, as is ſuppoſed, they made uſe of; and to be ſure, all the former Scriptures lately argued, are plain and preguant againſt any ſuch claim, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI.</head>
               <p>THere are ſome other things, that I will but lightly touch, though others of contrary ſentiment to you, will lay on load. One is, (at which I am not a little abaſh'd, as being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to defend, or ſo much as to excuſe it; notwithſtanding, I have heard what is commonly pleaded;) that though you, according to your declared Principles and ordinary Practice, are Non-conformiſts, and Diſſenters; yet upon occaſion, and to get into Place and Office of Honour or Profit, you will, and can Swear, Renounce, take all or any manner of Oaths, and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:52640:27"/>Teſts, that have of late been injoyned and impoſed; alſo, that you can, on ſuch occaſions, take the Sacrament according to the form and way of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> though you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did before, nor (perhaps) will ever do the ſame again; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept on the like occaſion; and although the making and firſt forming of theſe Oaths and Teſts, and the taking of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, were intended, and done on purpoſe to keep you, and ſuch as you, out of Office and Place, (whch how well done, and how according to Chriſtian Charity, I will not now diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute) yet by theſe ways, they have not been able to exclude you, and they think, and ſometimes ſome of them will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to ſwear, that they believe nothing, though never ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary unto you, and to your Principles, can be deviſed and made to keep you out, and conſequently, cannot hold you in, but that you will break all Bounds, leap over all Hedges, ſo that they are at a loſs what to do with you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. But, O! The horrible ſcandal that comes from hence, upon Religion in general, and to the Party you would ſeem to own, and eſpecially to your ſelves. This opens the Mouths, fills many Books and Pulpits, with matter againſt you; they ſtick not flatly to ſay, that you are as bad, and make uſe of the ſame Artifices as the Jeſuits do in ſuch caſes; and though it may vex them, to ſee you thus too hard for them, yet it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain relieves them by adminiſtring to them, and occaſion of venting their anger, and diſguſts againſt you; and withal, ſometimes it makes them merry and pleaſant, to ſee that they can find as bad (ſo they think) and as deceitful doings and practices among you, as among thoſe of the illeſt Name and Character: Perſons of thoſe Principles, which your ſelves uſe moſt to exclaim againſt, that is, the Jeſuits, and men of their Spirits and Deſigns.</p>
               <p>I proteſt, I cannot tell how to anſwer them, as to this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>i. e.</hi> To do it with truth and honeſty; I know what is pleaded and pretended to juſtifie it; who knows not? Let things be never ſo foul when men have done them, and ſtand declared for them, they will ſay ſomething; and in this caſe they pretend it is lawful, and they will prove it ſo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But at preſent not to enter into that Controverſie, whether it be
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:52640:27"/>lawful yea or nay; but ſuppoſe it, and that this thing could be ſaid with ſome colour, or ſome ſatisfaction to themſelves yet.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> I always thought that Chriſtians ſhould and ought to have regard to others, how they take and reſent things, ways and actions, and how far a thing may be of uſe, to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Chriſtian Religion and Goſpel, and how far other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe diſhonourable to it; and that this had been a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent rational, (as well as a moſt Evangelical) Rule in it ſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that every man ſhould not look altogether on things as they appear to himſelf, but alſo, how his ways and actions appear to other men, what aſpect they have upon them, and how they ſtand in their eye; otherwiſe I do not ſee how men can intend to adorn the Goſpel of our Lord and Saviour Chriſt Jeſus, which every man ſtands bound to do.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Suppoſe you could prove, what you have done in this matter to be Lawful (which I cannot yet ſee, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not believe:) What is this to the purpoſe among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, or wiſe and good men? Though this Principle reigns much in the World, and among the men of the World, yet I think the matter is plain among Chriſtians, that it ought not to be ſo; yea, I am ſure they are to be led by Principles of a more excellent kind, than to do things meerly becauſe Lawful; or to think to juſtifie themſelves, when they have done them, becauſe they can prove them meerly Lawful. One would think, the Apoſtles Rule were near at hand, and to be heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, not only becauſe Apoſtolical, but for the reaſonableneſs, goodneſs, and worthineſs of the Principle it ſelf. In 1 <hi>Cor. chap.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 12: <hi>All things are Lawful, i. e.</hi> many or moſt things are ſo, few things in compariſon are abſolutely in their own Nature Unlawful. <hi>But all things,</hi> though Lawful, <hi>are not expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient,</hi> or profitable, or uſeful, and (beſides Lawful) conducing to ſome good end and purpoſe, for the promotion of Goodneſs, of Peace, of Piety, and the Goſpel deſigns in general; and <hi>chap.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 23. He ſaith, <hi>All things are Lawful for me, but all things are not expedient or convenient,</hi> again, <hi>All things are Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for me, but all things edifie not,</hi> and I am ſure, ſcandalous
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:52640:28"/>things, and of ill Fame and Report cannot edifie, <hi>i. e.</hi> cannot build up men in Holyneſs, in Purity, in the Love of the Truth; but on the contrary, ſtumble them, and caſt them down. Now it is the edification of others, and not the ſtumbling or ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalizing of them, thereby to hinder them in their love and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of, and commuance in the truth, which is here preſſed, as is manifeſt in the whole ſcope of the Chapter, and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Argumentation in it; and is without diſpute, the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the next words immediately following, <hi>v.</hi> 24. <hi>Let no man ſeek his own, i. e.</hi> Only his own, or his own, apart from others good; but ſo do, and ſo mind his own ways, as to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Counſel, why hath not the Chriſtian World, and men that will be called Chriſtians learned this? Chriſt the great Lord of Chriſtianity taught it, and was himſelf, both in Life and Spirit, moſt exemplary in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Beſides, it is common among your ſelves, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn it in others, that they impoſe things upon you, meerly becauſe they are, or may be, in their own Nature Lawful. The truth is, there are a thouſand things. Lawful, that world be moſt abſurd, under ſome Circumſtances, to do, or put them in practice, and many things, or moſt things are Lawful in the general Nature of them, and as diveſted of Circumſtances, that yet when they come to be done, or put in practice, will be ſo inconvenient and unfit, that it may be as bad, and as abſurd to do them, as if they were utterly unlawful.</p>
               <p>The concluſion is, in ſhort, that a good Chriſtian neither will, nor ſhould do any thing in it ſelf unlawful, nor any thing, meerly and only becauſe it is Lawful: but will mind ſtill, the fitneſs, the profit, the uſefulneſs of them, as to thoſe Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances they fall under, when reduced to practice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> I do not ſpeak all this, becauſe I think ſuch Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Communicating, for a preſent advantage is Lawful; but ſuppoſing that it were ſo, yet is that alone no good Reaſon nor Argument for the doing of it. Neither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain do I meddle or concern my ſelf with the Law and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that injoyns theſe things, nor with thoſe Perſons, that ordinarily hold and practice them, being in the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:52640:28"/>of that Church, for whoſe ſake and intereſt they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned and impoſed; but I ſpeak to them who pretending Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity as their ordinary way, and choice to walk in, that look upon the Oaths and Renunciations, either as unlawful, or oppreſſive, and uncharitable; and yet on the occaſion, and meerly on the account, of a place of Honour and Profit for once, and to ſerve a turn, will ſwear, renounce, take the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, do any thing rather than miſs it, or for fear of loſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, or that they may ſave themſelves, or Party by it. If this be not ſcandalous, offenſive, and to Religion and true Piety deſtructive, I know nothing that is ſo. I know nothing that will more render you in the eyes of all, as men of flexible and profligate Conſciences, that can do any thing, and make you ſeem more like to ſuch, that are juſtly eſteemed the worſt of men. It occaſions men to hate both you, and all Religon, at leaſt that which you profeſs, for your ſakes; however, you and men in your Circumſtances, may turn and wind, move every ſtone, break their Brains, and their Wits, to find out diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and evaſions to ſalve their Conſciences and Reputations, yet the vulgar running ſence, will judge otherwiſe of you and them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> But the common Plea for thus doing and grand Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection againſt what is here ſaid, will be this. O! but if we ſhould not do thus; then no honeſt men would be in Place, none but looſe, prophane, wicked, Atheiſtical, Popiſh, or Toriſh men, would get in; and ſo we ſhould, or might loſe our Rights, our Liberties, our All; yea, perhaps our Lives too: But to this I anſwer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Suppoſe this, yea, and the worſt that can be ſuppoſed, yet muſt we needs do evil, that good may come of it? If it be not evil to do ſo in it ſelf, nor occaſions any evil, nor ſcandal, for you to ſwear, renounce, receive, why do you then not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily practice it, and ſo make no breach nor diviſion on that account? Yea, why do you do it ſo ſecretly, clandeſtinely, that it ſhould not be publickly known, if it be well and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully done? But if you think it evil, and ſo evil, that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not well, and upon other accounts joyn with it, nor with them with whom you differ in theſe things, it is to be wondered
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:52640:29"/>at, how you can do it, on the account you now do. Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I ſee not, but upon this account you may comply with any thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Why cannot you truſt God, the Living God, in his own way, but take ſuch unhallowed Courſes and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as theſe, to the great danger and diſgrace of Religion, and of your ſelves? Sure I am, if you have not Faith to truſt in God, going in plain honeſt ways, ye have no reaſon to expect his Favour in diſhoneſt and ſuſpicious ways and doings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> If this Procedure be according to Law, and the Law made to keep you out, why cannot ye be quiet, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to it, ſeeing there is no penalty for refuſing to ſerve or ſwear! And for being ſhut out of Offices and Places (as to ſome of them) a man would think it ſhould be a conveniency to be excluded and rendered uncapable. And it is apparent enough, that many, if not the moſt of you, would in ſome ſuch way exclude others, if the Power were in your hands, as Papiſts, and perhaps ſome other, whoſe Opinion and Practices in ſome things you like not. They do not compel you to take Office or Place, and then make you Swear and take the Teſt, but put thoſe Bars and Blocks in your way, that ye might not come into them, ſuppoſing that when they made them, they had laid them ſo directly contrary to your former declared Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Practices, that they ſhould certainly exclude and keep you out.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> There is great Cauſe and Reaſon to believe, that God will ſooner help and vindicate you, if there be damage and diſhonour in being ſhut out.</p>
               <p>I ſay, there is according to the Divine Procedure abundant more reaſon to believe, and ye may rather expect, that God will do for you in this plain honeſt way of proceeding without ſin and ſcandal, and in the declining of all ſinful and ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ways, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then think to find his help and bleſſing in ways of your own deviſing, not ſo plain and honeſt as they ſhould be, but at beſt doubtful and ſuſpicious; and therefore dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:52640:29"/>And God ſometimes will have men to truſt him with all, and he tryes them in ſome way or other, whether they will truſt him, yea or no, and whether they will walk in the plain path of Truth and Sincerity, or whether for advantage they will ſtep out of this Path, and leap over the Hedge: He doth this to prove them, and when they are proved, and found faithful, he ſooner helps and vindicates them in a way of patient ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, and conſtant continuing in well doing, than in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, wherein they think to amend themſelves, in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods and proceedings ſcandalous and dangerous. Surely, a good honeſt tender Mind and Conſcience that fears Sin and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, would not thus adventure to walk ſo near the Pits brink, but be rather ſtudious, how he may walk fartheſt from it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Moreover I cannot ſee, but that as it appears to be ſcandalous, and of ill Fame and Report, and very hurtful to Religion and Godlineſs, for men to enter into Places of Profit upon theſe Terms: So they alſo, who are active in the chooſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch men, who they know beforehand, muſt thus debauch their Conſciences, and do that, which at other times they would by no means do; I ſay, ſuch Chooſers or Electors muſt in ſome kind and degree, at leaſt, be guilty of the ſame evils or ſcandals with the other. For how can I put another upon the doing that, which I know is his ſtanding Judgment and Practice not to do? Or why ſhould I be any ways acceſſary or aſſiſtant to any man, to put him upon the doing that, which I my ſelf would not do, and think that he ſhould not? And certainly, upon the whole, all the good that is pretended to be aimed at, in ſeeking thus unwarrantably to come into Place and Power, is much overballanc'd with the evil attending it.</p>
               <p>To Conclude, I ſay, as before, men will ſtingle, and wrig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, make uſe of all their Wits and Strength, appear with all their Evaſions and Diſtinctions, to ſalve up ſuch a Practice; but if they would take half ſo much pains to conſider the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter on the other ſide, and lay aſide themſelves, and their own Intereſt, and follow that which is common, open, and plain, and appears ſo to all, to the vulgar, and to impartial men, and to enemies too, they whould do better, and appear honeſter, than now they do, and honour Religion, and the Goſpel of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:52640:30"/>our Lord Jeſus our Saviour, better than they do: in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>chap.</hi> 31. <hi>verſe</hi> 32. <hi>Whether therefore ye eat or drink, or whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ye do, do all to the glory of God, give none Offence, neither to the Jews, nor to the Gentiles, nor to the Church of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VII.</head>
               <p>I Note only one thing more, wherewith you are not only charged, but ſtigmatized, and publickly diſgraced, <hi>(viz.)</hi> with Folly and Phanaticiſm; as if you were a ſort of People above all others, of crazy Minds, Phanatick, and irrational Principles and Practices, as to matters of Religion; particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in the Matter of your Diſſent and Separation from the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Church, Government, Laws and Worſhip. Doubtleſs, Folly, Enthuſiaſm, and Phanaticiſm in Religion, are as diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and prejudicial to it on the one hand, as Prophaneneſs and Immorality on the other: And meeting with ſome witty wicked Minds and Perſons, unacquainted with the Principles of Religion, and Power of Godlineſs, doth more ſcandalize them than the other, and occaſion them to think, that no man can be ſeriouſly Religious, but Fools; and that to be devout, is a ſign of ignorance. I do believe, that you are much wronged in this Matter, by ſuch who care not what they ſay, or may ſay, what they liſt, having all the publick Favour and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance; and their publick approved Teachers, do not ſeem at all to diſcountenance, but rather themſelves uſe and encourage thoſe that do uſe ſuch opprobrious Names and Characters; (how they will anſwer it to God, and how they can make it agree to that Chriſtian Love, Meekneſs, Charity, and Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, they as Chriſtians would pretend unto, I know not by ill Names worſe than <hi>Racha</hi>) to revile, rail upon, expoſe, to the moſt ignorant and prophane, not only ſome few, but ſo great a Number and Party of men, and their Fellow Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and doubtleſs a Party; to ſay no more than plain truth, not inferior to themſelves, either for Number, Piety, Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:52640:30"/>or uſeful Living in their Place and Generation: I ſay, to do this doth too certainly ſhew a Spirit not at all agreeing with a Chriſtian Spirit, and makes them look too like men unacquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Divine Nature and Temper of our Lord Chriſt, whoſe Example, they and we ſhould always ſet before us, be imitators of, that ſo being in this, and in all Vertue, as we ought like unto him, when he appears, we may appear with him, becauſe we are like him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Therefore my only buſineſs and requeſt is, that you would do nothing that may occaſion this, but cut off Occaſion from them that ſeek it, and would be glad to find any thing whereby they might diſgrace and diſparage you, either in Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple or Practice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thridly,</hi> I know, and am aware, That in all Ages from the beginning of the World, and more from the beginning of Chriſtianity to this day, beſide divers other ways of Envy, Vexation, and Perſecution, uſed againſt the better part of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, evil men have ſtill deviſed, and given them Names of Reproach, Scorn, and Deriſion, cruel Mockings, as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to the <hi>Hebrems</hi> calls them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed, as one having a Devil, Mad, or Phanatick; our Lord went not without this Livery; and the firſt Chriſtians were called by way of Contempt, <hi>Galileans,</hi> and quite through all the Ages of the firſt ten Perſecutions, there were ſtill devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſome hideous or ridiculous Names and Characters, to note them by, and render them odious; and ſo all along through the Reign of Popery, and the Romiſh Church, they were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Hereticks, Lollards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to make them both odious and ridiculous; the ſame Spirit hath not failed in our days, ſince the Reformation, one while calling them Puritans, Preciſians, and now at laſt Phanaticks or Mad-men. But I ſay, I would not you ſhould give any Cauſe or Occaſion for it: Neither do I know any thing, on account whereof they ſhould ſo eſteem you, but that upon the ſame, were we to retaliate and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der evil for evil, we might ſtigmatize them in the ſame kind; yet if any do follow or imitate them in this, their Way and Practice however provoked to it, they ſhall not be juſtified by me, nor, I believe, by him, who is appointed the great Judge of us all, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:52640:31"/>Conſidering with my ſelf, what it may be, that may give any colour to them, thus to ſtile you Phauaticks, Fools, or Mad men, or how you come to be reputed either Phanaticks, or Enthuſiaſticks; as far as I can conjecture, the occaſions are ſuch as theſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That ſome of you are taken notice of, to deny the uſe of Reaſon, in matters of Religion; or to deny that we ſhould judge of the ways and procedures of God, about our Salvation, and in matters of Divine Revelation, by our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Underſtanding, or according to them, or according to ſuch Principles, that men, as men, are capable to judge by, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> To this, I ſay, that I find none or very few, that thus ſpeak, and hold; and if any have been ſo inconſiderate, or let fall in the heat of Diſcourſe and Argument, ſuch inconſiderate ſayings in their Books or Sermons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> againſt the uſe of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in matters of Religion, ſuch are but few, and I judge fewer than have been, and I hope fewer will be, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But on the contrary, divers of the Nonformiſts have writ, and ſpoken, and preached rationally on the behalf, and in the defence of the uſe of Reaſon in Religion, many might be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. I have ſeen one piece intituled, <hi>the Intereſt of Reaſon in Religion;</hi> and that moſt pious (whatever Enemies may ſay) and moſt induſtrious, indefatigable Servant of Chriſt Mr. <hi>R. B.</hi> hath complain'd of ſome, for this very thing that they have done much wrong to Religion, to make men think that no Proteſtants ſpeak Reaſon, but Socinians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if any be found ſo weak, thus to declaim againſt Reaſon, they may poſſibly be betrayed thereunto through their adherence to ſome particular Opinions that they take for Truth, and conceive they cannot be maintained upon common rational Principles, and ſo extravagantly exclaim againſt Reaſon it ſelf. But of this ſort of men, whether they be few or many, I am ſure they are as well Conformiſts, as Non conformiſts. The truth is, you ſhall hardly ſee any Party of men, that hold together upon the account of any particular Opinion, Intereſt or Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in Religion, and not uniting upon Chriſtian Principles, as ſuch, but that they will in ſome one kind or other, be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:52640:31"/>Phanatick, and for the ſake of their Party, Way, and Intereſt, deny men the free uſe of their Reaſon, as to the things they make the Principle Marks and Characters of their Party or Sect. <hi>(E. G.)</hi> The Popiſh Religion if you will be of it, you muſt in many things deny your Reaſon and Senſes too <hi>(E. G.)</hi> in the infallibility of their Church, and in the great and ſenceleſs Hereſie of Tranſubſtantiation, with many others: ſo to be admitted into ſome other Churches, you muſt in ſome kind believe, as the Church believes, practice as they do, ſay as they ſay, though it be never ſo plain againſt your own Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Underſtanding <hi>(E. G.)</hi> You muſt ſubmit to the Church or Eccleſiaſtick Power and Authority to ſuch Laws and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, becauſe, or for the ſake of the Authority commanding them, though the things in themſelves ſeem never ſo contrary to your own underſtanding, and to the beſt Judgment you can make of things; this I ſay, you muſt ſubmit to, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo unſatisfied; which ſeems contrary to all reaſon, to the Goſpel of Chriſt, and in it ſelf is moſt uncharitable and injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to Chriſtian men. Take almoſt any other Sect, Party or Diviſion of men, that ſeparate from theſe, they will have a <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> ſomething that muſt not be touch'd, that muſt not be throughly Anatomized and Diſſected, nor put upon the tryal of free Reaſon, and rational manly Principles, but muſt be taken for granted, as an unqueſtionable Principle in their way, as being the uniting Principle and Character of their Sect and Party.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> But becauſe I would come as near as I can, to the true meaning of thoſe that deny the uſe of Reaſon in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do grant, That there are ſome things, yea, many things, that through the infinite Grace of God, are revealed in the Scriptures and Goſpel of Chriſt: Indeed the whole Frame of it is ſuch, with the moſt excellent Methods and Counſels of it, that all the Wit of men, and Reaſon in the World, and all the Wiſdom, Sagacity of men and Angels could never have found out, or thought of; but now being revealed and made known to us, we can by our Reaſons and underſtandings conceive of them, are able to underſtand and judge of them, and though
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:52640:32"/>they were once, yet now they are no longer Myſteries, ſave ſo far as all things are Myſteries, till men will be at the pains to know and underſtand them, when all that Study, Care, and Prayer, which ought to be uſed, and to which the Promiſes are made, that according to ſuch endeavours, the Counſels of God in the Goſpel of Chriſt, ſhall be underſtood have been uſed; and eſpecially, if we live holily, cloſe with God, and walk up to that which we already know, God will in due time reveal all the reſt unto us, ſo far as we need know; and this not againſt, nor without the uſe of our Reaſons, but through the humble Exerciſe and Improvement of them.</p>
               <p>If any ſhall ſtill object, That there are yet ſome things, that cannot with all our Reaſon and improved Underſtandings be known, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I grant it may be ſo, eſpecially, to ſome, and at ſome times: But then as I cannot underſtand them, ſo it is no part of my Faith to believe them, but, I am to leave them as they are. I am not obliged to ſpeak about them, nor to practice them; and that which otherwiſe might be a Duty for me to do, did I know it, not knowing of it, now is not; and indeed, it is a piece of honeſty and ingenuity in a man, not to pretend to be knowing in more than he is, but to hold things for certain, that are ſo to him, and to live and practice them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly; and things that are but probable, ſo to hold and profeſs them, and for no other, and things doubtful, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs them as ſuch, that we do bout of, and to ſuſpend the Practice of them till better aſſurance and information be had. If this were done, men would be, and appear more honeſt and peaceable, and Diſputes and Conteſts about ſuch Points and Opinions, would be fewer and more moderate, and ſo need not hurt Peace, and hinder Charity, as now they too much do.</p>
               <p>In a word, happy were it, if men would be ſo free and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous, and the dogmatical and interreſted part of mankind would bear it, that every man would walk openly and honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, declare and profeſs, what he is, and what he thinks and believes, let it be ſomething or nothing, good or bad, he would the ſooner come to Information, and ſo be rectified, and in the mean time, would do leſs hurt, whereas while men keep ſuch
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:52640:32"/>things ſecret, they become hot and burning in their minds, they make more of them than they are, and when they have an opportunity to vent them, they are the more earneſt in it, do the more hurt by them if they be not good. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Whatever men think, and talk againſt the uſe of reaſon in matters of Religion, and of Salvation, yet certainly it is of ſo neceſſary a uſe, that they which talk againſt it, muſt uſe the beſt they have and can againſt it. It is ſaid of Juſtice, it is ſo neceſſary a virtue in humane life and affairs, that Thieves themſelves that live by injuſtice, Rapine and Wrong, yet are forced to make uſe of it, if it be but in diſtribution of what they have unjuſtly gotten: ſo men make uſe of their Reaſon whilſt they diſpute againſt it.</p>
               <p>I have heard of a witty Poem made againſt Wit and Reaſon, and in the praiſe of Folly; indeed the uſe of Reaſon can no ways be diſparaged and diſputed againſt, but by ſuch a Poetical liberty, or in the way of ſtark folly, if that could be ſuppoſed to do it.</p>
               <p>Again, Surely that muſt needs be moſt neceſſary, which a man, as ſuch, hath, and is eſſential to him, and without which he could not be a man, but ſome other Creature. Why a man ſhould be praiſed becauſe he is wiſe and rational, making uſe of his reaſon and underſtanding in all things elſe, onely laying it aſide in matters of Religion, which are his greateſt concern, and wherein above all things he had need uſe the moſt and the beſt of it, is wonderful ſtrange, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And further, moſt certain it is, that the ever bleſſed graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God, when he gives his Laws, and makes known his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels unto men, that he doth fit and ſuit them to the reaſonable minds and ſouls of men; that ſo men, as men, may conceive and iudge of them, and underſtand them. As he hath made all Creatures in their divers kinds, with ſeveral faculties of ſenſation and perception anſwerable to his dealings with them, and drawings of them; and his methods and inſtruments muſt be ſuited to them, that they be ſtirred and moved to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral works and ends; ſo Man above all other Creatures being made moſt free in his actions, and enabled to know and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what is ſaid to him, being alſo accountable to God his
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:52640:33"/>Creator for what he doth, and why he doth, muſts needs in his way and in a manner, proper to his kind, underſtand and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of divine things, which can be in no other way, than by his reaſon, whereby he is able to judge of the ways of God when made known to him, as well as other things; and therefore it is that God doth often appeal to men, and to their Reaſon and Judgment even, whether his ways be not equal, and their ways unequal; he makes them the Judges, which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he would not do, if they as men (only unbiaſſed and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial) were not competent for it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whereas ſome, to ſtrengthen themſelves in this conceit againſt the uſe of reaſon in Religion and divine things, do plead with all the reaſon they can allow themſelves ſome Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture paſſages; and in eſpecial that place in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. <hi>But the Natural man perceives not the things of God, for they are fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhneſs to him.</hi> The reaſon is given, <hi>becauſe they are ſpiritually to be diſcerned, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would not make any ſtay to open the Scripture at large, it needs not if men would be impartial, and it hath been done by others fully; and I would only deſire all ſuch that plead it, to mind theſe things, in the place, and about it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That what is ſpoken here of the natural, is meant not of the unregenerate man, but of the weak Chriſtian and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grown, or Babe in Chriſt, <hi>chap.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. And called carnal, that is, too much ſo.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the things of God here ſpoken of, which theſe could not receive, were not the common and moſt neceſſary things that were of abſolute neceſſity to ſalvation, but the high or deep things of God, which only the ſpiritual man or well-grown Chriſtian could well underſtand and comprehend: and by ſpiritual, according to the Apoſtles phraſe, is ſtill meant, ſuch as are well grown in Chriſtian knowledge, in oppoſition to weak men, and narrow-ſpirited Chriſtians: See theſe places in this Chapter, <hi>ver.</hi> 15. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 37. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That it is not here denyed, that ſuch a man could never know or underſtand theſe things, or that he was in an utter incapacity to underſtand them, but only this, that at preſent he was ſo; but this denies not, but that afterwards in a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:52640:33"/>of diligent endeavours he may know. As we ſay of one. That at preſent is not Book learned, he cannot read, nor underſtand Greek nor Latin, <hi>i. e.</hi> is in no preſent capacity for it; yet this hinders not, but that he may by diligence and ſtudy, applying himſelf to it; and by ſuitable inſtruction for it, learn and underſtand to do, what he cannot now do. Theſe things are plain in this Scripture, and in the Context about it; and if men will impartially conſider, and lay aſide all prejudice and prepoſſeſſions, they will find it to be ſo; and if not, they will never find any thing, nor the truth at all.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It is, and will be pleaded <hi>(viz.)</hi> That it is the Spirit of God that enlightens and gives inſtruction in Divine things, and that man cannot do, or know any thing without his aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and illumination, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I anſwer (1.) It is true, he doth ſo, and as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>No man knows the things of God but the Spirit of God.</hi> But (2.) beſides that he hath made known theſe already in that Revelation which he hath made of the mind of Chriſt at the beginning, ſo now he makes men to know and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the things of God, and helps every man that is willing to underſtand, and in ſincerity deſires it: but ſtill this is done not without (much leſs againſt) the uſe of their reaſons and underſtandings, but through them, and by them, he deals with men, as men, as reaſonable; ſo that they may underſtand and conceive of theſe in the ſame way they do of other things, though theſe be the moſt excellent.</p>
               <p>Again, it appears more plainly, to be thus, in that men are commanded and injoyned to ſeek, to try, to ſtudy, enquire, and labour after, the knowledge of Divine things, as well as, yea more than after other things, the which cannot be done but by the uſe of their reaſonable faculties as they are men, and thus they are helped, ſtrengthened, remembred, and every way aſſiſted by the Spirit of God, and more than they are in other things. And they want and ſtand in great need of this, partly becauſe of the excellent and inviſible nature, the dignity and ſoveraign concern of theſe things to men; partly alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of that backwardneſs, darkneſs, and weakneſs that cleaves to us, by means whereof we ſtand in greater need of care, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:52640:34"/>and humble Prayer to God, the Father of Lights, and the giver of ſuch good and perfect gifts. (3.) It is manifeſt, that the more we do in this kind, the more we receive; to him that thus improves, more ſhall be given; and the more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, or idle, or otherwiſe diverted by the things of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the leſs we receive at the hand of God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as we find by experience. In agreement to this, there are many precepts, injoyning us to labour, to ſeek, in order to the receiving this Grace; and many Promiſes and Encouragements thereunto, and conſequently our not doing of it, not thus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying of our ſelves to the work with all humble ſupplication, in all ſincerity, is the reaſon why we want it, and want the Divine Grace, which elſe would be more plentiful in it.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If we do not thus imploy our reaſons and underſtandings, in enquiring into the things of God, we are like to be deceived, and ſome other Spirit will get into us, that is not of God; and and ſo we are like to be miſled, turn'd indeed into the way of Enthuſiaſm and Phanaticiſm, as we ſee dayly it is with ſome. Yea, ſo clear and manifeſt it is, that what we receive of God, and the Goſpel of Chriſt, muſt be by and through the uſe of our rational faculties, that by them we are bid to try the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, whether they be of God or of men, or of a worſe inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by which thoſe are generally miſled, that think to find the Truth otherwiſe than in this moſt proper and neceſſary way. So that take the matter, and conſider it, how we will, it is manifeſt; the ordinary work and operation of God, and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God upon us in the making his will known, making of us to underſtand, and to be impreſſed with the knowledge and ſence of Divine things, or things of God, muſt be by and through the uſe and exerciſe of our reaſon judgments and underſtandings.</p>
               <p n="7">7. And finally, if any plead and contend that according to theſe proceedings, men may and do deceive themſelves; we daily ſee them run into great errors, hereſies, miſtakes, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding otherwiſe Rational and Learned, and pleading much for the uſe of Reaſon too. Suppoſe that thoſe be errors and hereſies, that you think are ſo, (for you may be miſtaken) but I ſay, ſuppoſing it to be ſo, is it any Argument becauſe
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:52640:34"/>men may abuſe and wrong imploy their noble Faculties of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and underſtanding, that therefore there is no uſe of them in any caſe? ſurely then we muſt all unman our ſelves. But that men may uſe and imploy all the powers of their Souls, and members of their Bodies to ſin and ungodly purpoſes, is no doubt, as neither is it, but that they may uſe them to good and uſeful purpoſes, ends and deſigns; which if they do not, ſeeing they may do it, they ſhall give a moſt ſevere account to God in this matter above all other. And the Truth is, the principal reaſon and account, of the juſt and ſevere judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and condemnation of God againſt men, that will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned at laſt, will be reſolved into this; that they have not improved nor made a right and honeſt uſe of thoſe natural and moſt excellent Faculties, which they have as men <hi>(viz.)</hi> that reaſon and underſtanding which God hath given them; and conſequently on the account of thoſe Talents, and Seaſons, and Opportunities of Grace, which they having received from God, for the doing good to themſelves and others, have neglected.</p>
               <p>Some againſt all reaſon object, that we are not to compare Heavenly things with Earthly, and Divine things with Carnal, which men will and are like to do, if they judge of the one by the other, according to their reaſons, and humane under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, to this I ſay in ſhort, that it is a wonder, that men can ſay and object this, when they ſee the conſtant way and reaſoning of our bleſſed Lord himſelf in his Parables and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons; and how he doth ſtill compare Heavenly things to Earthly, and illuſtrate them by theſe; ſtill ſaying, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven, or the Kingdom of God, (which is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Goſpel) is like unto this, or like unto that, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the way, reaſon, method, compariſon, and procedure of men, in earthly and natural things, and in the things of this life, as in the Parable of the Sower, and many other, which are too many here to ſet down, and plainer than that there ſhould be need to argue them.</p>
               <p>Only this, the Heavenly and Spiritual, or Divine things, differ by way of excellency, and of their ſoveraign uſe to men; but this hinders not, but that in their general nature and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:52640:35"/>of proceeding, they hold a proportion with them in the reaſon, evidence, proof, and demonſtration of them.</p>
               <p>To conclude, when I ſpeak ſo much (becauſe there is ſo much need) of the uſe and exerciſe of mens judgments and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings in matters of God and of Religion, as well as in other things: I hope none will think, that I ſuppoſe men In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, or that they may not either willingly, or ignorantly err, and do amiſs, and uſe them otherwiſe than they ought, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But only thus,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That an honeſt exerciſe and uſe of them, is the way wherein we are moſt certain to find, and may expect a bleſſing from God, in our enquiry and ſtudy, and good ſucceſs in the matter, and things enquired after; and this though it be not infallible, is the neareſt to Infallibility, and (we may be ſure) of the greateſt certainty, whereby to come to a right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; and be ſurely led in the things of God, and of our everlaſting concerns.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That men may be diſhoneſt, and ſuffer their hearts and minds to be byaſſed and wrong influenced, and darkned; they may not love the Truth, for Truths ſake, they may have their Intereſt and their Luſt to gratify, and ſo they may err and do ill, and the Spirit of God may be grieved and kept at a diſtance, and not help them, nor ioyn with them: But if they are of honeſt ſincere minds, which all may and muſt have, even the weakeſt as well as the ſtrongeſt, they will find they may be ſurely led; and no other but ſuch, have the promiſe for it, and ſo far they are kept out of the way of the evil Spirit as well as from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of their own Spirits, and from the ſubtilty and deceiving of Evil and Intereſſed men.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Some of you are charged with Phanaticiſm, ſometimes in your Prayers and Sermons, <hi>i. e.</hi> with divers odd, and too courſe, blunt, and over-familiar, and unbecoming words and Phraiſes, Compariſons and Similitudes, which ſeem nauſeous to ſome, Ridiculous to others; and however paſſable among the People, out of their reſpects to you, yet offenſive and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Ears of the more Judicious, and give occaſion more than you think for (but ought to conſider) to others to ſcoff, deride, and thereby countenance and confirm themſelves in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:52640:35"/>what they are willing enough to believe. <hi>(viz.)</hi> That you are, as they call you Phanatical, and men of abſurd Speeches, and ſometimes of Behaviours in your Religious Exerciſes: And though this may as well be charged upon others, and ſome of your Accuſers as well as any; yet they having the advantage of you in State-Favour, and being otherwiſe more in the Faſhion than you are, they can make that uſe of it againſt you, which you cannot againſt them, neither ought if you could; and this ſhould make you the more careful, with the greater Piety and Prudence, to manage all things of a Religious nature, with ſuch a comelineſs and decorum, that you may diſparage neither Religion, nor your ſelves. And though ſuch kind of runnings out may not diſpleaſe, but ſometimes rather pleaſe, delight, ſome of the more Raw and Ignorant ſort of People, yet to the Judicious, even among your ſelves, they are offenſive, trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and make them ſomewhat abaſhed: Certainly men may ſpeak ſo as to avoid all affectation, quaintneſs, pedantique Jing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on the one hand; and alſo all abſurd, unhandſome, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comely utterance and expreſſions on the other; and what is ſpoken on ſuch occaſions, may be ſober, ſerious, rational, and manly. But of this I ſhall take no further notice, having done it before.</p>
               <p>Only I cannot chooſe but wonder, that you having heard and ſeen ſo much of this nature objected againſt you, both in Speeches, Diſcourſe, and in Printed Books (which will inform, and word it to you, better than I can) ſhould not now be more careful in it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Something of this nature is noted of you in and about the performance of Religious Duties, and about the taking up ſome private Opinions, Notions and Practices in Religion, upon the account of a new pretended Revelation, or new impulſe, ſtrong and extraordinary motions upon your Spirits.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, as to Religious Duties and Services, This is charged on you (and by ſome, too much occaſion is given for it:) That you will not pray, (to give that as an inſtance for the whole) or go about any ſuch Religious Service, till you are firſt ſtrongly and inwardly moved to it, or as ſome ſpeak, have an impulſe upon their minds, or be moved by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:52640:36"/>and when ſuch a forcible touch or ſtrong motion is upon their minds, right or wrong, they account it a moving of the Spirit of God, meerly, becauſe they are ſtrongly moved and perſwaded. And if ſuch a Motion be not, they reckon and do account, they are not obliged at all to the performance of any Duty; in anſwer to this, conſider,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> I grant, That Chriſtians may at ſometimes be ſtirred and moved in their Spirits, to ſome religious Work and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, more than at another time, and that he that is ſo, doth well, to take and not to omit ſuch an Opportunity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But</p>
               <p>That he ſhould not ſet upon the performance of Prayer, or any Chriſtian Service till he is ſo ſtirred and inwardly and ſtrongly moved; this is a Doctrine and Perſwaſion, than which nothing is more fooliſh, and pernicious, or Phanatick (if you will have it ſo:) very dangerous to the Souls of men, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more contrary to ſound Reaſon, nor the holy Scriptures. And this is ſo plain, that it is a wonder any conſidering man ſhould be perſwaded to it, or led by it. For in how many places doth the Holy Ghoſt, ſpeaking in the Scriptures, call upon men to ſtir up themſelves to their Duties, to gird up the Loyns of their Minds, to be ſober, to conſider, and to watch and pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yea, to provoke themſelves, and to provoke one another unto good Works, as they ſee Cauſe and Reaſon for it; how often are we called upon, to ſtrive, to run, to wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, and that againſt our ſelves? how often, and how vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently are we called upon to pray? (to ſpeak to that Duty; particularly, as an inſtance of all the reſt,) abundance of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments are uſed, to provoke and inforce men to be conſtant, diligent in it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What need all this; and abundance more that's ſaid, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage us to beſtir our ſelves if this need not be done, till we are inwardly ſtirred and moved, and muſt wait for ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe and inflation of a mighty Spirit, to raiſe our minds unto it; nay further, do not theſe earneſt Charges and Exhortations plainly ſuppoſe and prove, that men may by the ſerious thoughts of their Duties, the Reaſons, and Neceſſity thereof, ſtir and raiſe in themſelves ſuch a ſtrong Motion, to the Duty they ſpeak of? Again,</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:52640:36"/>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Do not the Scriptures ſpeak much, and give men to underſtand, and make them aware of their own dulneſs, and backwardneſs to this, and all good Works and Duties? and doth it not admoniſh them, and put them in fear, leſt a cold, flat, indiſpoſed Spirit grow upon them; ſo that at laſt they may come to be hardened and deceived, that in ſeeing, they may think they ſee, but not indeed perceive? In hearing, they may think they hear, but not underſtand, and that their eyes may come to be cloſed, that they cannot ſee. And is not this a moſt dangerous and dreadful ſtate, which men come unto by neglect, and by not being diligent, earneſt, conſtant and ſervent, in ſtirring up themſelves in, and to all holy Ways and Services? And it matters not, as to the danger and dreadful effects coming thereby, whether theſe come by minding other things, and by their being ingaged in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent World, or whether they come through a vain Phanatick, Enthuſiaſtick perſwaſion, that they are not to act in religious Duties, except extraordinarily moved to it; for ſtill a neglect there is, from what cauſe ſoever it comes, the danger and ill effects are the ſame. That this ill and inſenſible Spirit, is the effect of ſuch Enthuſiaſtick Notions or Apprehenſions, is moſt manifeſt in our days; and to that paſs, by theſe means ſome come, that they neither pray by themſelves, nor pray or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God in their Families; they neither pray with them, nor for them, nor for any, except ſome extraordinary motion puts them upon it, and ſo at laſt they Worſhip, not God at all, neither in publick, nor as far as any can underſtand in private; and in fine, do hardly profeſs, or give any account of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief in Chriſt Jeſus, nor whether they be of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or of any Religion, or whether they be only Civil Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans; you ſhall ſeldom hear them mention the Name of Chriſt Jeſus, with any reverence or expreſſions of any tolerable Love and Affections to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Becauſe theſe kind of men, before they come to be ſo bad, do ſeem to reſt much upon the motions of the Spirit of God, as they pretend. (For indeed) to ſpeak the truth, there are extreams on both ſides; for as theſe will do nothing without ſuch motions and impulſes, others, on the other hand
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:52640:37"/>reſt too much in their forms of Devotions, or in their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Parts and Abilities, and ſo do not look for, nor ſeriouſly attend unto, nor pray for the Divine Illumination, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of the holy Spirit, who certainly, to humble ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere minds, waiting on him, and asking his help, will never be wanting.</p>
               <p>But I ſay, ſeeing ſuch extreams and miſtakes there are, let us ſee, what the Scriptures teach us, and what we may rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably expect of Grace and Aſſiſtance in this kind, to help us in all holy Chriſtian Works and Services; and we find the Holy Ghoſt is often ſpoken of in the Scripture, eſpecially in the New Teſtament, as an helper and aſſiſtant to us, in the things of God, and of Chriſt Jeſus, as, <hi>E. G.</hi> for the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of them, and our Illumination in them, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance and bringing of them, and all fit things unto our minds, for the helping of us in the performance of them; and becauſe our weakneſs, ignorance, and indiſpoſedneſs is great, and our infirmities many, ſtill accompanying us in all Religious Services, and eſpecially, in the Work and Duty of Prayer (which is that we gave for an inſtance for all the reſt,) I ſay, it is plain and manifeſt enough, that the Holy Spirit of God is promiſed to us, and doth concern himſelf in us about theſe things, but we are no where taught, that ordinarily his Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are of ſuch a hot and ſtrong Nature, that we cannot reſiſt them; but on the contrary, that men do reſiſt him, and that his Operations may be reſiſted, and as to the Effect fruſtrated; he may be grieved and depart from us, not being entertained by us as he ought: And that his Motions are ordinarily ſoft and ſtill, not coming in a Storm, not in Thunder, or with a Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, but ſuch, that by men, careleſs, earthly, lovers of, and buſie in this preſent World, or otherwiſe indiſpoſed, or ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed, may not be felt or underſtood, becauſe not attended unto, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That his Motions and Workings in us, are, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways muſt be, in and by our Reaſons and Underſtandings, as we are men; becauſe, by the faculties, we as men, are indued with, and according to them, we muſt judge, whether ſuch Motions are good or not, whether the things and works we are
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:52640:37"/>put upon, and moved to, are good, fit, ſeaſonable, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently uſeful, orderly and comely, whether for edification to our ſelves, or profit to others; we are to know, conſider, and judge of the quality of thoſe Motions, and to underſtand our ſelves, leſt we follow an ill Spirit, as well as the good and holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God. Finally, conſider, we ſerve the infinitely Wiſe God, that takes no pleaſure in Fools, nor in inconſiderate Works, Ways, and Worſhips, unleſs we know what we do and why. A meer Motion, therefore or Impulſe, or ſtrong Inflation and Work upon the mind, is not to be followed without further Tryal and Judgment paſs upon it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> And in particular, when we ſpeak of the help and quickning of the Spirit of God, eſpecially, in our Prayers, it is not needful, nor have we any good Reaſon, to expect that he ſhould dictate to us, the very words and expreſſions we are to uſe in them; but the things and matters we are to pray for, with neceſſary and fit Arguments, by which our Prayers are preſſed and inforced, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So when we come to conſider our ſtate and condition, and what things we have to pray for, it is then proper for the holy Spirit to bring thoſe fit and apt things to our minds, eſpecially, to do this upon great and weighty occaſions, and in times of great neceſſity and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, which that place, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. ſeems to have a ſpecial reſpect unto. And again, we have great need of this Divine help, to raiſe and to bear up our hearts, and to maintain a Spirit in us, both conſtant and fervent, and to keep us from deadneſs, and formality, and to mind us what we have prayed for, and what we have in deſign, that we may purſue it to the utmoſt, till we have obtained what we deſire; and further, by his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Motions and Aſſiſtance, to help us againſt the flatneſs and dulneſs of our hearts, and to ſtir us up, to a continuance and inceſſantneſs in it, with many other needful helps, as occaſion is and requires, both in this of prayer, and in all other things reſpecting the perſeverance and ſafe conduct of a Chriſtian Life, in order to Eternal Life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventhly,</hi> It is not to be denyed, but that at ſome times, there may be occaſion, (but very rarely) to work upon, to move and act ſome men at a more than ordinary rate, as the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:52640:38"/>Prophets and Apoſtles were at ſome times, when they had ſome extraordinary Work to do; but this, I ſay, if it be at all, muſt needs be rare, extraordinary, and ſeldom done. Conſidering,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That there needs now no new Revelation of the mind and will of God, what he would have us to do, and to believe, ſeeing that all this is fully made known by Chriſt Jeſus in his Goſpel, who was ſent on purpoſe to make known the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect will of God, and did at the firſt in a moſt plentiful man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſend down his Gifts and Endowments upon men, to fitthem for the ſame Work which himſelf had laid the Foundation of. So that there can be no frequent need and occaſion for extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Revelations and Motions. If there be any thing yet remaining of an extraordinary Nature, there may be expected extraordinary Aſſiſtance, but for our ordinary Duties, belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a Chriſtian Life, and to the keeping of the Commands of God, to the glorifying of God our Heavenly Father, and for the walking worthy of ſuch a Calling, as we are called unto; we are to learn from the Scripture, and to give our ſelves to the ſtudy of them, with underſtanding and judgment, learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and drawing our duty from them, together with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Nature, Excellency, and Dignity of the things we are to underſtand, the things of God, and of Eternal happineſs, and herein we have the Promiſe, and may expect to receive the help of the Divine Spirit, in and by the means of our Study and Enquiry, only it is neceſſary we be ſincere, ſober, and conſiderate about ſuch matters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Suppoſing that which is not, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that ſuch ſtrong motions and impulſes ſhould be vouchſafed and allowed, for the ſtirring of us up to our ordinary daily Works and Duties, ſuch as Prayer, Meditation, Devotion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Suppoſe, I ſay, that we needed not go about them, till ſuch motions were ſtrong upon us; though this were true, as it is not, yet this were not the beſt, nor the moſt excellent way of Obedience, nor of the performance of any Duties, or good Works, but a kind of weak, low, and childiſh Obedience, in them that would not, could not ſtir until they were forcibly led, and that could not upon the appearance of the reaſon, neceſſity, and occaſion of the Duty, ſet themſelves about it, or know
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:52640:38"/>when to do it. Out of doubt it muſt be judged the moſt free, moſt generous, and excellent kind of Obedience, to do and ſet about our Duty that we know to be ſo, though we feel no ſuch powerful motions, nor ſtrong inclinations to it, as long as our Reaſons and Conſciences are convinced of it that it is to be done. Knowing our Duty in the general, we ſhould (according to that common light and wiſdom, and the ordinary vouchſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God unto us) be willing ſometimes to ſtir up, and to compel our ſelves to our Duty, or any good work we have to do, and what in our knowledge and Conſcience we ought to do, though we ſhould find our ſelves unwilling, or, as we ſay, going againſt the hair, <hi>i. e.</hi> the preſent diſpoſition, inclination, and temper of our ſpirits.</p>
               <p>But if we muſt ſtill wait for extraordinary Motions, and not many times go againſt our Minds, when they are contrarily bent and indiſpoſed, as too often they are, what mean, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides our own experience) all thoſe great Charges and Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions-preſt upon us, to ſtir up our ſelves, to gird up the loins of our Minds, to ſhake off ſloth, or not to be ſlothful, but vigorous Followers of them, and of that which is good; to be intent and earneſt in it, though we have averſation and indiſpoſition to it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now may not all ſee, that this is the moſt free, the moſt excellent, generous, reaſonable, and conſequently the moſt acceptable, and well-pleaſing way of obedience, in which not following our natural, or ill diſpoſitions, or indiſpoſitions, we purſue, what, according to the Divine Law, and our Duty, we are bound to do, whether it go with us, or againſt us. And the more we deny our ſelves, and go againſt our ſelves, the more we ſhew of Reaſon, and of Reſolution, and of entire Devotion, Reſignation of our ſelves unto God, and to his ſervice: Is not this, I ſay, the moſt excellent, and therefore the moſt acceptable way of obedience and performance of all Religious, and Holy Services?</p>
               <p>I might add to what hath been ſaid, ſomething about the ſpirit of Phanaticiſm, as to Opinions and Tenets in Religion and matters of Faith and Doctrine. Some ſometimes take up new and ſtrange Doctrines, meerly upon the account of ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:52640:39"/>ſtrong motion and perſwaſion that is upon their minds. They think they are Divinely inſpired, becauſe a thing is ſet home upon their hearts; and this conceit as wild as it is, hath produced many ſtrange Notions and Opinions that have been born and brought forth into the world by it. The Heat of the Brain, and the Strength of Fancy have been the Parents: and though upon no better a foundation many Diſciples have been made, and the Authors have had many followers.</p>
               <p>Such was the beginning of many Sects among us, ſuch was the firſt riſe and beginning of ſeveral of the Orders of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church; for the ſame Spirit works both in them, and ſometimes in thoſe that would ſeem moſt oppoſite to them; and whoſoever will be at the pains to read Hiſtories both Civil and Eccleſiaſtical, may find not a few of this kind; and if you will but be at the labour to read ſome pieces written purpoſely on this Subject; as Dr. <hi>Merrick, Cauſabon</hi> of <hi>Enthuſiaſm;</hi> and Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> of the <hi>Phanaticiſm of the Church of</hi> Rome, and others of this Nature, you may have enough, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This wild Spirit hath ſeemed to ſhew it ſelf moſt at the beginning, or ſoon after the Reformation, or ſome change in Religion, as it was when Men began, in great Numbers, to fall off from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Popery,</hi> and at ſome other time ſince amongſt <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>When Men are newly come out of Darkneſs and Ignorance, and begin to ſee the Light, which not having been uſed unto, they ſeem to be for a while in a maze, not well knowing where they are, nor how to ſix themſelves, and ſo run out into extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies of Opinions and Fancies, without Reaſon, without End; or elſe, when they new come out of their former Bondage and Slavery, wherein they have been tyed as to Religion, and their Conſciences, and begin to taſte Liberty, and the ſweet of it, they often grow wild and extravagant, ſo that no ſober bounds of Reaſon and Religion can hold them. And feeling the Reins now upon their Necks, with which they have been pinched, and too ſtraitly held in, they now run on, while they are quite out of breath: They deviſe new Opinions, and ſpawn new Sects at no Aim.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:52640:39"/>Which thing conſidered, might be a good Caution and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition to them who have, or pretend to have the Reins of Eccleſiaſtick Power in their hands; and ſuch who take upon them to guide and rule others in matters of Religion and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. This, I ſay, might be an Admonition to them, while they are in Power, to deal gently with thoſe under them, to draw them and drive them, as they are able and willing to go: For though ſome through Fear and Force, and ſometimes for Intereſt, will go on, and ſwim with the ſtream, and go in the Crowd, yet ſecretly in their minds, they hate and diſtaſte, if not deteſt it. And though for their preſent either Eaſe or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, they comply and ſubmit to the yoke of their hard Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; yet this ſomewhat galling their Necks, perhaps their Conſciences, as ſoon as ever they can get looſe, and be at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from under this Bondage, remembring their late forced Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance, they commonly become the greateſt Enemies to their old Maſters, and above all others, are moſt fierce againſt them. Yea, thoſe who never complied, but were clear Diſſenters from them, commonly are not ſo great Haters, fierce and implacable Oppoſers as theſe: For they having not only ſtoopt againſt their Wills, but againſt their Conſciences too, in ſome kind, they now know not how ſufficiently to revenge themſelves againſt their Drivers. The experience of our former Troubles, beſides the reaſon of the thing it ſelf, is a ſufficient Proof of this: But from what Cauſe ſoever it is, this is certain, when Men break looſe from under the hands of tyrannous and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Men, few of them can keep in temperate Bounds; for being rid of the common Enemy to them all, every one of them are ready to ſet up for themſelves, ſome into one way, ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another; ſome deviſe new Opinions, whereby to make a new Sect or Party, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And among the many Occaſions and Temptations this way, this is frequently found to be one, they either are perſuaded themſelves, or pretend to it, and endeavor to make other Men believe, that they have ſome new Revelation, and what they do is by Divine Inſpiration; which thing, for the ſuppoſed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, honour and ſingularity of it, invites and tempts great
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:52640:40"/>Numbers after them, to which this doth not a little contribute, in that they now ſee, what little or no reaſon their old Maſters had to claim ſuch a Power and Authority as they uſed and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed over them. And they cannot alſo, but eaſily and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee this, that they have full as much Authority to guide and govern themſelves to take their own courſe, in chuſing of their own Religion, Sect, or Opinion; yea, and more than their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Lords could juſtly pretend, and lay claim unto, for the Rule and direction of thoſe they had under their Power. Therefore certainly it would well become all that are in Place and Power either in Church or State, when they intermeddle, and concern themſelves in Religion, and go about to direct and guide Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences in it, that they would make this moſt evident to them, that the Power they exerciſe, and the Things they command and enjoin, are moſt clear and evident, upon the moſt undoubted Principles of Reaſon and Religion, ſuch as are either really, or upon the matter ſelf evident, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Finally,</hi> This ſtill ſeems to have been the Method and Policy of the Devil and evil Angels, proceeding from that great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and envy they have unto Men, becauſe of the great mercy of God ſhew'd unto them, <hi>viz.</hi> That in the firſt place they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to debauch the Souls and Conſciences of Men, and to turn them quite off from God, and to draw them (if poſſible) through the vile Sinks and Channels of all Filthineſs, Pollution, and Prophaneneſs; unto all abominable Sin and Wickedneſs, both of fleſh and ſpirit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if this be not ſo feaſible always, but that ſome Men will be ſober, ſerious, and perhaps Religiouſly inclined, yea, devout and zealous, then they lay the train of their Temptations an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other way, and in another vein, more ſuitable to their Nature and Tempers, and find out for them, and fill them with ſome fine Notions, and curious Speculations, with ſtrange Doctrines, and ſome new deviſed, or new revived Opinions and Hereſies, and make them believe that theſe matters newly revealed, and brought to their minds, ſet home upon their ſpirits, are from and by the Spirit of God, and that God hath in a ſpecial manner revealed and honoured them to be the Authors or Preachers of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:52640:40"/>them, and ſo they increaſe and propagate, and being carried on with great heat and confidence, and in the Name of God, and being Novelties, which the Vulgar are not acquainted with, they are much affected therewith; they take them up both eagerly and haſtily, and will by no means have the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, nor the prudence, to have any thing ſeriouſly tryed by plain Scripture and Reaſon; or however will not hearken with calmneſs, and without prejudice, what may be ſaid to it, and againſt it, but run away with it, being loth to loſe the honour of a new-diſcovery, and of being the firſt promoters of it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>THus Chriſtian Friends I have taken a liberty (but no other than the common concern of every Chriſtian will allow) to mind you of ſome things wherein you may be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, or thought ſo to be: I neither have, nor dare take upon me ſo much Authority or Confidence to reprove, judge or condemn you for the matters here taxed; but only I take my obſervations from others, and from not ſo much private as publick reproofs, nay from the ſcorn and deriſion ſome make at thoſe things they think reprovable in you, publickly expoſing you on thoſe accounts: Your Friends being in the mean time heartily ſorry that you take no more notice thereof, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are your reputed enemies, and ſuch you account looſe and prophane (though you cannot think they are all ſo) that have publickly, and in Print thus expoſed you; you have not endeavoured ſeriouſly to look into your ways, and to conſider whether ſomething thus noted, may not ſtick to you. Remember that we all conſidered, both as men, and as particular Sects and Parties, are better ſeen by others than by our ſelves, and ſhould not haſtily and out of prejudice and ill opinion reject the reproofs and admonitions, no not thoſe that
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:52640:41"/>are done out of malice and hatred, and perhaps with ſcorn, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and revenge, knowing that though ſuch may overdo, yet are like enough to light upon what is true as well as falſe, becauſe they will take all that is to be found or ſuſpected: But I aſſure you, ſome of your Friends, and ſuch who agree with you in the ſame cauſe of Nonconformity, have with grief and regret obſerved ſome of theſe faults and defects, eſpecially thoſe about too much Formality amongſt Profeſſors and Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, thinking ſo well of themſelves for, if not glorifying in their Party, and way of Diſſent and Separation, without thoſe real Fruits, holy Diſpoſitions, and ſuch Chriſtian temper of Spirit, in all Peace, Meekneſs, Humility and Sanctity, and ſuch good works that ſhould grace the Chriſtian Profeſſion, and cannot be reproved, but may be underſtood and approved of all, even the worſt of men: And they are not a little troubled at the folly, Fanaticiſm and Enthuſiaſm of ſome of you, (though others of all Parties may be guilty as well as you) and the lack of that manly wiſdom in managing your Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Profeſſion, and thoſe rational both Principles and Practices that might adorn it, the want whereof diſgraces it altogether.</p>
            <p>It hath been before noted, that folly or Fanaticiſm is as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graceful (and in ſome reſpects worſe) to the Honour and Beauty of the Chriſtian Profeſſion, as Prophaneneſs and Irreligion; both of them and in the ſame point, have the ſame ill effects upon the Prophane and Negligent part of mankind, eſpecially men that are Wittily wicked; the Scriptures, eſpecially of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> caution as well againſt the one as the other, and againſt the Former of Folly and Fancy, in all thoſe places where we are cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned not to be Fools, but to be wiſe; not weak, nor Children in underſtanding; ſo not in practice, but to be wiſe and walk wiſely, to be knowing and underſtanding, what that good, moſt perfect, moſt acceptable will of God is, that we may do it; and we are bid to have Salt in our ſelves, and to be ſober and ſerious, wiſe and prudent, with abundance of this kind, and eſpecially to take care of this in our publick Worſhip, and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour of a Religious nature. You would do well to look ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly into your Principles and Opinions, and the conceptions you have of God, and of the things of Religion, that there be
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:52640:41"/>not any error or miſtake about them, that may betray you into theſe ways of Fancy and Enthuſiaſm.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I confeſs it is ſometime ſince theſe Papers, and the Addreſs to you was firſt drawn up, that there may have been ſome Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations in ſome Matters and Affairs relating to you (as every day will alter ſomewhat;) and that you may think ſome Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities have been uſed towards you ſince; but I hope this ſhall not make you to loſe any part of your Patience, Prudence, or Charity, but by ſuch exerciſe to improve in them, and to let patience have her perfect work, <hi>James</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 4. that you may be entire, wanting nothing; and if any want either wiſdom or patience, let him ask of God who giveth liberally to all; but be well and throughly reſolved that what you ask you are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to follow and practice, and not wavering, nor unreſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved whether you had beſt have it or not, for then you ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive nothing, <hi>ver.</hi> 6, 7, 8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Further, 'tis my deſire that you would be more compaſſionate to them you think hurt and moleſt you, then concerned for your ſelves; not to be angry or offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with them, but to learn what Spirit you are to be of towards your enemies, and to learn of him who is the great pattern and exemplar in this and all Divine vertues, even our dear and to be adored Lord and Saviour in his Precepts commanding us to love our enemies, and to pray for them that deſpightfully uſe us and perſecute us; not to return evil for evil, no not in words re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling for reviling; with abundance more to this purpoſe: And himſelf was the excellent example in this, yea when he was upon the Croſs in the midſt of his Torments, and ſurrounded with his Tormentors, with ſcornful revilings, cruel mockings, and the higheſt provocations (and I think under the moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el hard circumſtances, all things conſidered that ever any was) yet in the midſt of all did not ſo much mind himſelf as them, his Charity and Compaſſion was greater for them than himſelf, and moſt heartily praying for forgiveneſs of them: And that we may not think this only proper for him, and that no other could do the like, or imitate him in it, conſider that beſides his Example, that we are to follow his Command (and ſurely he would not command it if we were not by his Grace in a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city to do it.) We have alſo an inſtance of one of his Servants,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:52640:42"/>a man with like paſſions with our ſelves, <hi>Stephen</hi> the firſt Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, who when he was in the throng of his violent Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners actually ſtoning of him, yet then was moſt mindful of them, and prayed heartily for them, having well learned of his Lord and Maſter. You have not yet ſuffered much; 'tis good for Chriſtians, and their duty, to be prepared for the worſt, which the Chriſtian ſpirit will moſt excellently fit them for: And be ſure in all your Prayers to God, there be not the leaſt tincture of hatred againſt your enemies, or uncharitableneſs or ill will againſt any, for this will ſpoil all, and the good ſucceſs of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Neither is it well done, (though too many are faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in it) to trouble your ſelves with fears and jealouſies, of what Evils will come, what Alterations, Changes, and Revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may be in the World, or amongſt our ſelves, the fears of Popery, and the great Troubles that muſt needs follow there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon. Not to be ever careful in any of theſe things, but in theſe, and in all, to commit your care, and the care of all, and the publick, as well as your own private, unto God by Prayer and Supplication, and leave it with him, truſt him with it, and the peace of God ſhall keep your hearts and minds through Chriſt Jeſus. Hinder not your ſelves in the enjoyment of your preſent peace, nor by a diverſion of your mind, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling your ſelves about theſe ſuppoſed and feared Events. Your preſent great work and care of working out your Salvation, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the greateſt care and fear above all, and in this, as well as other things, let your moderation be known unto all men, and whatever may by the Providence of God, or evil of men, fall out, that may diſpleaſe and trouble you in matter of State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changes, be you not diſturbed nor provoked to any Diſpleaſure, Diſcontent, much leſs, Tumultuouſneſs, and Violent Motions: but be as Chriſt Jeſus, whoſe Kingdom not being of this World, was not, would not be concerned in the Affairs of it, much leſs, to diſturb the Publick, and State Affairs in it; ſo ſhould his Servants, they have other work to mind, and enough to do, to carry on the Affairs of his Spiritual Kingdom in their own hearts, and to promote it in the World, in all his ways of Goodneſs and Charity, in Meekneſs and Piety, in Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:52640:42"/>in Well-doing, and patient Forbearance and Suffering. Finally, what I have writ here, and ſaid, I have done it in the Fear of God, and in Love and Charity to all, being deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to do what I can to honour the Goſpel of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and to my Power to warn you againſt the things that are diſhonourable to it: And I conſider, that the deſigne of God in the Goſpel of Chriſt, is, that after the Revealing, Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Publiſhing of it, it ſhould be next carryed on, by the holy Lives, and worthy Walking of thoſe that profeſs it, and commended to the World that way, and that the Light of your good Works and holy Living ſhould ſhine before men, that you ſhould ſo manage your Chriſtian Profeſſion, both in your private Capacities, and as Members of the Chriſtian Church; and that by this means you may prevail, and do more good than with all Profeſſions, Preaching, or any other Services otherwiſe you can do; yea, ſo powerful is holy Living, that they that will not be perſwaded by the World, may be won by the excellent Converſation of Chriſtian Men and Women. I might here cite abundance to this Purpoſe, even the whole new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament-writings, but this is plain, and well known: Happy are we if we do it: To conclude, all ſhould look more at god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and worthy walking, and for the promotion of Piety in the World, than to any particular part of Religion, Opinion, or Party of their own; but this is not yet well learnt nor taught as is too evident among the ſeveral Sects, Parties, and diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſtians among our ſelves, and elſewhere; for moſt are more intent upon their own way, than upon the main de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the Chriſtian Religion, and ſo are ſtill looking about for ſuch particular Paſſages, and Texts of Scripture, ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Precept, Command, or Example, that may favour their own Way, Opinion, or Party, and hack and hew at theſe, cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them off from their main body, and grand deſigne of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, whereas being taken, as they are, and ought to be, in Conjunction with it, and interpreted according to, the main principle Duties of Godlineſs, Peace and Charity, and the advancement of real Righteouſneſs and Goodneſs, the ſence and meaning of all ſuch particular Parts and Paſſages, would become eaſie, and be better underſtood, and that aſpect
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:52640:43"/>and influence they have upon the whole, would be better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and the minding the great Intent and purpoſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, would enlighten them, and ſo Contentions about them would ceaſe; Love, Charity, and Goodneſs, would be joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly promoted and carryed on by all, and the common good and Salvation of men, furthered for the moſt part, the conteſts in Religion are but about the leſſer things, <hi>viz.</hi> outward Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Rites, ſome ſmaller and leſs conſiderable Opinions and Practices, all which would be ſoon ended, if Chriſtians of all Sects and Diviſions, would but mind the main; if their Paſſions. Luſts; and evil Affections were mortified, and their Love and Charity to all were more warm, and if they would ſtill mind what is beſt to be done, and wherein they may beſt approve themſelves to God, and to men; herein alſo would they find the greateſt Peace and Satisfaction in themſelves, and acceptation with God, and the righteous Judge of all, Jeſus Chriſt our Lord at the laſt. I end all with the excellent Rule, laid down in <hi>General,</hi> comprehenſive, Terms, Phil. 4.8. <hi>Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Brethren, whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are honeſt</hi> (decent or ſeemly,) <hi>whatſoever things are juſt</hi> (or Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,) <hi>whatſoever things are pare, whatſoever things are lovely,</hi> (or Friendly,) <hi>whatſoever things are of good report, if there be any Vertue, if there be any Praiſe, think upon theſe things.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
